<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Hadadrimmon, sive, Threnodia anglicana ob regicidium a sermon on Davids humiliation for cutting off the royal robe, and detestation of cutting off the royal head of the Lords anointed : preached Jan. 30, 1660, being a solemn fast for the horrid murther of King Charles I of glorious memory, at Westbury, in the county of Wilts. / by John Paradise ...</title>
            <author>Paradise, John.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1661</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 173 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 30 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A55721</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P327</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R13634</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13021047</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13021047</idno>
            <idno type="VID">96629</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A55721)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 96629)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 394:22)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Hadadrimmon, sive, Threnodia anglicana ob regicidium a sermon on Davids humiliation for cutting off the royal robe, and detestation of cutting off the royal head of the Lords anointed : preached Jan. 30, 1660, being a solemn fast for the horrid murther of King Charles I of glorious memory, at Westbury, in the county of Wilts. / by John Paradise ...</title>
                  <author>Paradise, John.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 52 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J.H. for Nathanael Webb ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1661.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Errata: p. [6].</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
                  <note>Marginal notes.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Charles --  I, --  King of England, 1600-1649.</term>
               <term>Memorial service.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:96629:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Hadadrimmon, Sive <hi>Threnodia Anglicana ob Regicidium,</hi> A SERMON ON <hi>DAVIDS</hi> HUMILIATION For Cutting off the ROYAL ROBE, AND DETESTATION of Cutting off the ROYAL HEAD Of the LORDS ANOINTED.</p>
            <p>Preached <hi>Jan.</hi> 30, 1660.</p>
            <p>Being a Solemn Faſt for the <hi>Horrid Murther</hi> of KING CHARLES I. Of Glorious Memory, At
<hi>WESTB<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RY,</hi> in the County of WILTS.</p>
            <p>By JOHN PARADISE Preacher of the Word there.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>J. H.</hi> for <hi>Nathanael Webb</hi> at the Sign of the Kings Head in St. <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard. 1661.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:96629:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:96629:2"/>
            <head>TO THE Right Reverend Father in God, HUMPHREY, By the Providence of God, LORD BISHOP of
<hi>SAR<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>M.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Reverend Father in God,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Emorable, if not Miraculous, is the Story con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Dumb Son of <hi>Croeſus,</hi> how that ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing an Aſſaſſine about to kill his Father, though he never ſpoke before, yet then cried out, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: So our Political Father, <hi>Cor, Sol, &amp; Anima Regni,</hi> the <hi>Heart, Sun</hi> and <hi>Soul</hi> of the Kingdom, being tranſlated from us, in a <hi>Fiery Chariot,</hi> Who can but cry out with <hi>Eliſha, My Father, My Father, the Chariot of Iſrael, and the Horſemen thereof?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Should Subjects neglect to ſing the <hi>Obſequies</hi> of their Murdered King, the
<hi>Wals</hi> of the <hi>Royal Palace</hi> would be mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numents of their ſhame; even as the
<hi>Stones</hi> would have ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied the defect of the Childrens Hoſanna's to the Son of God; &amp; the <hi>duſt</hi> of the ground where the <hi>bloudy Tragedy</hi> was act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, would teſtifie againſt them, as the <hi>duſt</hi> of the <hi>Apoſtles Feet</hi> againſt the unbelieving <hi>Jews.</hi> Seeing Rebels have been ſo induſtrious in forming <hi>Cyclopical Weapons, in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velling</hi> out Diabolical <hi>Machinations</hi> againſt Monarchy, and have publiſhed ſo many bitter Invectives and <hi>Satyrical</hi> Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels againſt the Sacred Perſons of Kings, to <hi>enchant</hi> and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toxicate the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation, and to ſeduce us from our Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance, God forbid that we ſhould omit the Confection of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tidotes, and Counter-medicines againſt this Poyſon.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:96629:3"/> Wherefore I have attempted to vindicate the <hi>Royal Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative</hi> of King<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> wherewith they are inveſted by a <hi>Divine Charter,</hi> and which is a Jewel fixed in their Crownes by the King of Kings, to wit, <hi>Their exemption from the vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence of Subjects;</hi> and likewiſe (though indeed the Acts and Monuments of our Royal Martyr deſerve rather to be registred by the Golden Pen of ſome Able Martyrologer, another <hi>Fox</hi>) to commemorate that <hi>Fatal Blow,</hi> which cauſed an <hi>Earth-quake of Deſolation</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> and as it were <hi>unhinged</hi> the <hi>Earth</hi> from its
<hi>Center.</hi> The Lord grant, that it may now produce an <hi>heart-quake</hi> of Lamentation, and prove d Lymbeck to <hi>diſtil</hi> our hearts into tears, to extract the
<hi>Quin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſſence</hi> of our ſpirits, and to <hi>ſublimate</hi> our Affections, and Faculties into the height of Sorrow.</p>
            <p>Now my Lord, the Beams of your Favour <hi>accented</hi> and <hi>enamelled</hi> with manifold
<hi>Amplifications,</hi> have ſo influent <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally ſhined on me, that they cannot but work <hi>indelible</hi> Impreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of Gratitude in my heart, unleſs it were <hi>petrefied,</hi> and moſt ſtrenuous endeavours after teſtification thereof.</p>
            <p>Wherefore I preſent unto your Lordſhip this enſuing <hi>Book of Lamentations,</hi> as a
<hi>Pepper-corn</hi> by way of acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of my great Obligations unto you: Humbly imploring your candid Acceptance and Patronage of this unpoliſhed piece, in imitation of the Divine Majeſty, who accepted of Badgers Skins, Goats hair, a Cup of cold water, and the Widows Mite, as well as more magnificent Oblations. As I am conſcious of many Imperfections, which your judicious eye will diſcern herein, ſo I am confident of your Indulgence.</p>
            <p>I have endeavoured more to manifeſt the <hi>Affection of my heart,</hi> then the
<hi>Affectation of Art. Sackcloath</hi> and <hi>Aſhes</hi> is a fitter Garb for Mourners, then
<hi>Gorgeous Attire.</hi> Who can be eloquent on ſuch a <hi>doleful Theam,</hi> as the Murder of a Christian, Proteſtant King, which like <hi>Opium</hi> is enough to <hi>ſtupifie</hi> the the Faculties of all that ſtudy on it? and at the Tidings whereof, (as <hi>David</hi> wiſhed for
<hi>Abſalom:</hi> O my Son <hi>Abſalom,</hi> my Son, my Son <hi>Abſalom:</hi> Would God I
<pb facs="tcp:96629:3"/>had died for thee, O <hi>Abſalom,</hi> my Son, my Son) Your Lordſhip with many more
<hi>Engliſh</hi> Hero's, could (I believe) have cried out, <hi>O my King</hi> Charles, <hi>my King, my King</hi> Charles: Would God I had died for thee, O <hi>Charles,</hi> my King, my King.</p>
            <p>I think it Honour enough, to be vouchſafed, to bring but one Pin to the decking of Christs Spouſe, while others adorn her with more coſtly Jewels, and rich Medals, ſaid a Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Biſhop: So I account my ſelf ſuperabundantly honoured, if this <hi>Threnodia</hi> may be accepted by my Dread Sovereign, through your Lordſhips Interceſſion, as the ſmallest Testimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of my <hi>Cordial Lamentation,</hi> for the <hi>barbarous Decolla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of his Royal Father, though but like the <hi>caſting a Branch of Roſemary into a Grave,</hi> while others erect more <hi>Glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Tombes</hi> and Statues; and as a pledge of my great exul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, for his own Happy Reſtauration and Coronation.</p>
            <p>My Lord, it is my Intention, to write an <hi>Euchariſtical,</hi> not a <hi>Panegyrical</hi> Epiſtle; becauſe I know, that Flattery, as it is <hi>abhorred</hi> by my ſelf, ſo it would be <hi>nauſeated</hi> by your Modeſty. However, without contracting any ſuch guilt or cenſure, I may record it for your perpetual Renown, That while ſo many have proved <hi>Erratick Stars,</hi> ſomtimes <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grade,</hi> ſomtimes <hi>Retrograde,</hi> never
<hi>Stationary;</hi> you have been a <hi>fixed Star</hi> in the Firmament of the Church of
<hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land:</hi> And while others have courted their Sovereign, with <hi>Paraſitical</hi> Friendſhip, for ſaking him in Adverſity, as <hi>Rats and Mice do a Barn, when the Corn is ſpent,</hi> your Soul hath cleaved (like <hi>Jonathan, Ittai, Barzillai</hi> and <hi>Zadok,</hi> to diſtreſſed <hi>David</hi>) to an <hi>afflicted Prince;</hi> that you have reverenced the
<hi>Setting Sun of Marty<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed Majeſty,</hi> King
<hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt, and the <hi>clouded Sun of exiled Majeſty,</hi> King
<hi>Charles</hi> the Second.</p>
            <p>I have read concerning <hi>Agrippa,</hi> that being impriſoned for wiſhing the Empire unto
<hi>Caius,</hi> he was afterwards gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified by <hi>Caius</hi> with a Chain of Gold, as heavy as that of I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron, wherewith he was loaded in Priſon: So, that your
<pb facs="tcp:96629:4"/>Lordſhip, who have <hi>magnanimouſly</hi> endured the <hi>Malignant Influences</hi> of <hi>Blazing Comets,</hi> during the diſmal <hi>Eclipſe</hi> of the <hi>Proper Light,</hi> may as a Bleſſing unto the Church of God. long ſit under the vivifical and ſalutiferous Beams of our <hi>Royal Sun, now Triumphant in his Noon-day Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> is the Prayer of,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Lordſhips moſt Humble Servant, JOHN PARADISE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Errata.</head>
            <p>Pag. 2. Line 37. read. <hi>Renowned.</hi> p. 3. l. 18. r. <hi>Engedi.</hi> p. 3. l. 14. r.
<hi>Abſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loms.</hi> p. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. l. 29. r.
<hi>ingenuous.</hi> p. 6. l. 3. r. <hi>connivence.</hi> p. 6. l. 13. r. <hi>worn.</hi> p. 8. l. 22 r. <hi>Bloud of Charles,</hi> ib. l. ult. r. <hi>Iſaac.</hi> p. 12. l. 32. r. <hi>edge of your humiliati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi> p. 15. l. 33. r. <hi>Martial.</hi> p. 20 l. 31. r. <hi>There can be no Adulterer without an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dultereſs.</hi> p. 23. l. 21. dele <hi>of</hi> after <hi>Glory.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:96629:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>THRENODIA Anglicana ob Regicidium, OR THE LAMENTATION Of Loyall Subjects, for the DECOLLATION of their Royall <hi>Sovereign.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>2 Sam. 24.5, 6.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>And it came to paſſe afterward, <hi>Davids</hi> heart ſmote him, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he cut off
<hi>Sauls</hi> Skirt.</p>
                  <p>And he ſaid unto his men, The <hi>Lord</hi> forbid, that I ſhould do this thing unto my Maſter the Lords <hi>Anointed,</hi> to ſtretch forth my hand againſt him, ſeeing he is the Anointed of the <hi>Lord.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">J</seg>Ulius Caeſar</hi> being <hi>brutiſhly murthered,</hi> in the Senate houſe,
<hi>Marcus Antonius</hi> brought forth his bloody Coat to the people of <hi>Rome,</hi> ſaying,
<hi>behold the bloody Coate of your Emperour;</hi> who at the ſight hereof ſo <hi>Condoled</hi> his death, that they fell into a furious rage againſt the murderers: ſo <hi>King Charles the firſt being inhumanely mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered</hi> at the Gate of his Palace, I am this day to <hi>revive</hi> the memory, and <hi>Repreſent</hi> the barbarouſneſſe of this doleful <hi>Tragedy,</hi> and as it were, <hi>to hang forth his bloody Robes before your eyes;</hi> that all your hearts may be ſtirred up to Godly
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:96629:5"/>humiliation, for this horrid murther of our ſacred Sovereign, the breath of our Noſtrils, the Anointed of the Lord: and therein <hi>the beheading of three Kingdomes.</hi> For the <hi>Wiſh</hi> of <hi>Nero</hi> (which was, <hi>That all the Citizens of Rome had but one Neck, that ſo he might kill them all at one blow</hi>) was fulfilled <hi>to,</hi> and executed
<hi>by</hi> our <hi>Engliſh Neroes;</hi> who at once ſevered the <hi>Royal Head</hi> of King
<hi>Charles</hi> from his <hi>own Body natural,</hi> and <hi>our body Politick; leaving England, Scotland</hi> and <hi>Ireland</hi> in a <hi>bleeding, dying</hi> condition, on that <hi>fatall birth-day</hi> of <hi>Englands miſery Jan.</hi> 30. 1648. This dreadful <hi>doomſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day</hi> (if, I may ſo call it) among all the daies, ſince the creation, next to that, wherein Chriſt was crucified (were it not vain to curſe a day irrevocably paſt,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi>
1.3, 4, 5, 31. <hi>Job</hi> 3.3, <hi>to</hi> 10.</note> and ſinfull to curſe a day that God hath made,) doth chiefly deſerve to have ſuch <hi>Anathema's thundred</hi> out againſt it, as
<hi>Job</hi> pronounced upon the day of his Nativity. We may affix ſuch a motto unto it, as
<hi>David</hi> unto the day of <hi>Abners murder, Know ye not that a Prince and a great man is faln this day in our Iſrael?</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 3.38.</note> Wherefore Pious and Chriſtian is our turning it into an <hi>Anniverſary Faſt,</hi> that the Nation by ſolemn and ſorrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful lamentation, may diſcharge it ſelf from the guilt, and avert the puniſhment of this Royal blood, which was ſhed in the midſt of it. That I may contribute ſomething thereunto, I have choſen this Text to be the foundation of my enſuing diſcourſe, which being ſo ſuitabe to the ſeaſon and occaſion, may challenge the honour, that
<hi>Solomon</hi> gives to a word fitly ſpoken,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prov.</hi> 25.11.</note> namely, <hi>to be like Apples of Gold, in pictures of ſilver. Theſe Golden Apples</hi> require little <hi>paring</hi> by explication; my chief work will be in the doctrinal, and Applicatory parts, to cut and quarter them forth unto you, for your edification in Loyalty.</p>
            <p>The words are <hi>Hiſtorical,</hi> being a part of <hi>the Chronicle,</hi> and
<hi>Narrative</hi> of the perſecution of <hi>David</hi> by <hi>Saul,</hi> the ſum, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of is briefly this; <hi>Heroical David</hi> having out of <hi>zeal</hi> for the weal of his country, through his <hi>Wiſdom proweſs,</hi> &amp; the <hi>bleſſing of</hi> God <hi>crowning</hi> his enterpriſes with <hi>ſucceſſe,</hi> performed many <hi>glorious ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploits,</hi> particularly that famous <hi>victory</hi> over <hi>Goliah</hi> the great gyant of Gath, <hi>Who defied</hi> the armies of Iſrael, and of the living God; with many more honourable
<hi>atchievements</hi> againſt the Philiſtines, was <hi>Admired</hi> and <hi>Renouned</hi> among the people, <hi>Inthroned</hi> in their affections, and <hi>applauded with Superlative acclamations;</hi> yea, (through the <hi>indiſcretion</hi> of the vulgar,<note place="margin">1
<hi>Sam.</hi> 18.7.</note>) above the King himſelf. <hi>Saul hath ſlain his Thouſands, and David his ten thouſands.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Saul</hi> ſeeing his own glory thus <hi>extenuated</hi> and <hi>eclipſed,</hi> while
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:96629:5"/>Davids <hi>ſhined forth ſo brightly, envieth</hi> Davida praiſe,
<hi>fear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ch</hi> his perſon, is
<hi>jealous</hi> of his fidelity; leaſt by reaſon of his <hi>popularity</hi> he ſhould carry on ſome ambitious deſigne for his own acceſſion to the Kingdome; and therefore purſueth after his life (knowing that, <hi>mortui non mordent</hi>) thereby to prevent the peoples revolt, and Davids heading them. <hi>So dangerous is honour, that it often proves the ſnare and ruine of the perſons dignified therewith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Though this act of Saul may ſeem a neceſſary <hi>piece of ſtate-policy</hi> to a
<hi>Machivilian eye,</hi> yet certainly to the eye of a <hi>Christian,</hi> it will appear a groſſe violation of <hi>Piety;</hi> For David had given many demonſtrations of his unfeigned loyalty, but never any ground of ſuſpicion of intended Rebellion, by abuſing his intereſt in the affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of the Iſraelites. The imitation of Davids integrity by our late popular Abſoloms would have been <hi>Englands happineſſes</hi> as their <hi>deviation</hi> from his footſteps, was our miſery.</p>
            <p>The perſecuted, having eſcaped, many <hi>ambuſhes</hi> laid for his life, at length findeth his <hi>perſeoutor,</hi> at a great advantage, in a <hi>Cave</hi> at <hi>Engedy:</hi> but ſpareth his life, cutting off only the Skirt of his gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>Thus having taken a ſurvey of the Suburbs of the Text, I am now arrived at the words themſelves: which contain,</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>Davids Cordial contrition for cutting off the Royal Robe of King Saul,</hi> ver. 5. where conſider,
<list>
                  <item>1. <hi>The great degree of his ſorrow. His heart ſmote him.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. The <hi>ſlight nature</hi> of the Act (conſidered <hi>materially</hi>) for which he mourned, It was his cutting off the <hi>Robe,</hi> not the <hi>Head</hi> of <hi>Saul.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>Davids Loyal Deteſtation of outting off the Royal head of the Lords Anointed, manifeſted in</hi> a ſuccinct, and excellent Orati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>ver.</hi> 6. wherein may be conſidered.</p>
            <p>Firſt, The <hi>occaſion</hi> thereof; which was twofold.</p>
            <list>
               <item>I. The fit <hi>oportunity</hi> he had to ſlay Saul, being in a Cave.</item>
               <item>II. The great <hi>Importunity,</hi> wherewith his Souldiers perſwaded him thereunto.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Secondly The <hi>Orator,</hi> He (i. e. <hi>David</hi>) ſaid unto his men.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. David a <hi>Subject.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. David a <hi>General</hi> of an Army.</item>
               <item>3. The <hi>Auditours,</hi> he ſaid unto his <hi>men, i. e.</hi> his
<hi>Souldiers.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>4. The <hi>Oration it ſelf:</hi> which may be <hi>Analyzed</hi> into 4. parts.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>I. A vehement detestation. The Lord forbid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>II. The Act deteſted,</hi> That I ſhould do this thing, to ſtretch forth my hand againſt my Maſter.</item>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:96629:6"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>III. The perſon deteſting this Act,</hi> that I <hi>(i. e. David)</hi> ſhould do this thing.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>IIII. The reaſons of his Deteſtation;</hi> which are deduced from <hi>Sauls Relation.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>To himſelf — My Maſter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>To God — the Lords Anointed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. I ſhall begin with <hi>Davids Cordial Contrition, for cutting off the Royal Robe of Saul;</hi> And from the greatneſſe of his ſorrow, and the ſlightneſſe of the Act, which was the ground thereof, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared together,<note place="margin">Obſerv.</note> Obſerve,
<q>
                  <hi>That the leaſt diſloyal action, the ſmalleſt injury, and ſlighteſt indignity, committed againſt, and offered unto a King, ought, by Godly ſorrow, and true Repentance, greatly to be lamented. Davids heart ſmote him, becauſe his hand ſmote Sauls garment.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Though David being himſelf ſurpriſed, with his ſudden, and unexpected ſurpriſal of Saul, in ſuch a place of advantage, did (through <hi>incogitancy,</hi> and <hi>inadvertency,</hi> not thinking there had been any evil in <hi>ſpoiling</hi> the <hi>garment,</hi> ſeeing he
<hi>ſpared</hi> the life of Saul: And likewiſe out of zeal for the vindication of his innocen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy) adventure on an Act unbeſeeming the <hi>Majeſty</hi> of a <hi>King,</hi> and the
<hi>Duty</hi> of a <hi>Subject:</hi> yet as ſoon as he <hi>recollected</hi> his thoughts, and conſidered, that not only the <hi>perſons,</hi> but the <hi>Robes</hi> of Princes, (which are the <hi>Enſignes</hi> and <hi>Badges</hi> of authority) ought to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main untouched; and found his
<hi>action criminal,</hi> and himſelf <hi>culpable,</hi> his heart ſmote him.</p>
            <p>As <hi>Ephraims</hi> repentance is ſet forth by his <hi>ſmiting</hi> on the
<hi>thigh.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jer.</hi> 31.19. <hi>Luke</hi> 18.13. <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.57.
<hi>Act.</hi> 2.37.</note> The Publicans, by <hi>ſmiting</hi> on the <hi>Breſt. Peters, by weeping bitterly.</hi> The ſorrow of the converted <hi>Jews</hi> for their crucifying Chriſt, by being <hi>pricked at the heart. So Davids Remorſe</hi> for woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the robe of his Sovereign is expreſſed, by his <hi>Hearts ſmiting him. Compunction</hi> of ſpirit for the
<hi>leaſt</hi> diſloyal actions ſhould al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies follow the <hi>commiſſion</hi> of them.</p>
            <p>A Loyal ſubject being overcome by a violent temptation may be <hi>induced</hi> to Act ſome things <hi>Derogatory</hi> to his <hi>Kings Honour,</hi> and <hi>his own Loyalty;</hi> yet when by
<hi>deliberate reflection</hi> thereon, he diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerneth his crime; he will expiate the guilt by true repentance. Even as water, though it be hot, whilſt ſet over the fire, yet when removed from thence, returns to its priſtine coldneſſe; and as an he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ie Body violently detained from its center, <hi>Remoto prohib<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nte,</hi> naturally and immediately deſcends thereunto.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:96629:6"/> Loyalty may be <hi>ſullied,</hi> but cannot be <hi>obliterated, ſmothered</hi> for a time, but never <hi>totally exſtinguiſhed.</hi> It may be
<hi>wounded,</hi> but can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be <hi>Killed; fall aſleep,</hi> but will <hi>awake again,</hi> and like the <hi>Sun</hi> breaking forth out of a <hi>Cloud,</hi> appears in its
<hi>brightneſſe</hi> and <hi>glory</hi>-David being conſcious of his clemency towards the life of Saul, might have excuſed his cruelty towards his garment: but ſo pure and
<hi>Chriſtalline</hi> was his Loyalty, that he ſeems to forget his <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parallel compenſation of good for evil;</hi> and wholly <hi>Dwels</hi> on this <hi>Punctillio.</hi> Thus S. Auſtine in his confeſſions ſaith, that he was troubled in conſcience for ſtealing Apples in his youth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Moderation in diſloyal actions, is no ſufficient Apology for them.</hi> Had David urged this plea, he might have rather juſtified himſelf, for doing no more; then accuſed himſelf, for acting ſo little. He might have expected to have been <hi>Commended,</hi> rather then
<hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned;</hi> ſaying, Saul hath no reaſon to be <hi>offended</hi> with me for
<hi>cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting off his garment,</hi> but <hi>much reaſon</hi> to reward me for <hi>not cutting off his Head.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Should a <hi>Thief</hi> finding a <hi>Thouſand pounds</hi> in Gold, in a travel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers purſe, take away only <hi>ſix pence,</hi> leaving all the reſt untouched; yea, and afterward be troubled in his minde for thoſe ſix pence; it would argue eminent honeſty. This is the neareſt <hi>Embleme</hi> and reſemblance of Davids Heroical innocency; which yet did
<hi>ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mount</hi> this inſtance: The Law alloweth no <hi>Acceſſaries</hi> in the caſe of treaſon; all are principals. The Law of God adjudgeth them guilty, whoſe hands were only
<hi>inch-deep;</hi> as well as thoſe, whoſe hands were <hi>Elbow-deep</hi> in the blood of King
<hi>Charles.</hi> Men view<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their failings in the <hi>Crack't glaſſe</hi> of ſelfe-love, and through the falſe <hi>Spectacles</hi> of ſelf-juſtifying pride, account little <hi>Sins, no ſins, and great ſins little ſins.</hi> David was of a more <hi>ingenious</hi> and
<hi>impartiall</hi> Spirit; chooſing rather to aggravate, then extenuate, to <hi>magnifie</hi> then to <hi>mince</hi> the violation of his Allegiance.</p>
            <p>A Thief if he leave mony enough in the traveller; purſe to car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry him to his journies end, thinks himſelf to deſerve praiſe, rather then <hi>diſpraiſe:</hi> but an honeſt mans conſcience wil ſmite him, ſhould he wrong a man in the ſmalleſt matter, though he did it ignorantly.</p>
            <p>David knew that <hi>Diſloyalty</hi> is of an <hi>incroaching</hi> nature; that <hi>little ſins</hi> are <hi>gradual approaches toward greater:</hi> that if he could have diſpenced with wounding the <hi>Royal Robe,</hi> he might at length have adventured to wound the <hi>Royal heart</hi> of his Sovereign. Though <hi>Treaſon</hi> appear but as a <hi>ſparke</hi> of fire at firſt; yet if not quenched with the tears of repentance, it will ſoone <hi>flams</hi> forth
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:96629:7"/>into open <hi>Rebell<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s;</hi> and ſpread over the whole body <hi>Politick</hi> as the <hi>Gangren</hi> creeps from <hi>joint to joint,</hi> over the whole body <hi>naturall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Should <hi>indulgence, connivance,</hi> and <hi>Impunity</hi> be afforded, to an
<hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignity</hi> (though never ſo <hi>diminutive</hi>) againſt a King, it would
<hi>animate</hi> &amp; imbolden men to Act <hi>ſuperlative enormisies. Petty-larce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny</hi> is a
<hi>preparative</hi> to <hi>felony;</hi> it is <hi>felony</hi> in its <hi>infancy.</hi> He that can without remorſe ſmite a King with the <hi>ſword of his tongue,</hi> will, when opportunity ſerveth, ſmite him with a <hi>ſword of ſteel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As <hi>ſmal bruſh-wood</hi> is firſt laid on the fire to kindle the <hi>great Blocks</hi> afterwards laid upon it; and as the <hi>leſſer wedges make way</hi> for <hi>greater,</hi> ſo little ſins are but <hi>ſhooing-horns</hi> to draw on greater; and <hi>Dwarf-like crimes,</hi> but <hi>ſtirrups</hi> and <hi>footſtoolls,</hi> whereby to <hi>mount up</hi> on
<hi>Gigantick</hi> ones. Garments when the <hi>Hems</hi> are <hi>wore off</hi> will ſoon
<hi>unravel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Deſpiſing</hi> of Kings will grow to <hi>Depoſing</hi> of them, and
<hi>contemning</hi> of them, to <hi>condemning</hi> of them, if not checked betimes, either by the
<hi>Magiſtrates ſword,</hi> or the <hi>Offenders own conſcience:</hi> even as the
<hi>Cockatrices egg</hi> will <hi>grow</hi> to a <hi>Serpent,</hi> if not <hi>craſhed</hi> in the
<hi>Shell.</hi> For contempt of a Prince, is Regicide in the <hi>Bud,</hi> in the ſhell; and actuall Regicide is but <hi>Contempt full-blown</hi> and <hi>hatched.</hi> Wherefore laudable was Davids relenting for ſo ſmall an injury offered to his Prince. But let me correct my ſelf; why do I ſpeak of ſmall injuries offered to Kings, when the ſlighteſt indignities in themſelves, yet when committed againſt ſuch ſacred perſons, become <hi>hainous, flagitious</hi> and <hi>inexpiable.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The tranſcendent and incomprehenſible greatneſſe of God, cauſeth the leaſt offence againſt his infinite Majeſty to be of an infinite guilt; ſo that dignity, which the ſupream Jehovah, hath conferred on his deputed &amp; ſubordinate Deittes, doth cauſe the moſt inconſiderable offences againſt them, to ſwel up into high Treaſon.</p>
            <p>There can be <hi>no little ſin;</hi> becauſe there is no <hi>little God</hi> to ſin againſt: So there can be no <hi>Diminutive Treaſon;</hi> becauſe the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject thereof is the
<hi>ſacred, and honourable Perſon of a King.</hi> An Act receives its <hi>ſpecification, Denomination,</hi> and <hi>aggravation</hi> from the nature of its <hi>Object.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Uſe.</hi> This Doctrine doth conclude, a <hi>forti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ri</hi> for our <hi>lamentation</hi> this day, for that <hi>fatal</hi> and <hi>mortal blow</hi> that was given to our <hi>Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Sovereign.</hi> If the wounding of King Sauls Robe, the ſmiting of his skirt, caſt David into ſuch pangs of ſorrow: much more ſhould the cutting off King <hi>Charles</hi> his head; the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:96629:7"/>of his heart, cauſe England to mourn
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n Sackclotheand Aſhes. How ſhould the memory of this murder <hi>bedew Engliſh checkes,</hi> with teares, fill our hearts with ſorrow, and over-ſhadow us with mourning? as the <hi>Departing Sun</hi> doth the night with
<hi>Darkneſse;</hi> and the <hi>Declining Sun</hi> the Winter with <hi>Cold and Froſt.</hi> In
<hi>Ramah</hi> there was a voice heard, weeping, and mourning, and great lamentation: Rachel weeping for her Children, and would not be comforted; becauſe they were not.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 2.18.</note> And all by reaſon of the cruel <hi>infaticide</hi> acted by <hi>Herod.</hi> So in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> was there a voice heard, <hi>weeping,</hi> and
<hi>Mourning</hi> and great <hi>Lamentation:</hi> Subjects weeping for their King, and would not be comforted, becauſe he <hi>was not,</hi> and all by reaſon of the <hi>bloody Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gicide,</hi> committed by cruel Herods.</p>
            <p>We find in <hi>ſacred Hiſtory</hi> that ſubjects have bewailed all <hi>diſaſters</hi> bef illing their <hi>Kings,</hi> eſpecially their violent death.<note place="margin">2
<hi>Chron.</hi> 35.4, 5.</note> All <hi>Judah</hi> and <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> mourned for
<hi>Joſiah:</hi> And all the ſinging men, and ſinging women, ſpake of <hi>Joſiah,</hi> in their lamentations unto this day, and made them an ordinance in Iſrael.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Zac.</hi> 12.10. <hi>compared with. Acts.</hi> 2.36, 37.</note> Yea ſo great was their ſorrow, that the holy Ghoſt accounts it a fit pattern and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblance of that grief which ſhould poſſeſſe the hearts of the converted <hi>Jews,</hi> for their crucifying the Lord of glory. They ſhal mourn over him whom they have pierced, as a Father mourneth for his only Son. And in that day there ſhall be mourning, as the mourning of <hi>Hadadrimmon</hi> in the valley of <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giddon,</hi> which was the place where <hi>Joſiah</hi> was ſlain. If the Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſites thus lamented the death of <hi>Joſiah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Chron.</hi>
35.22.</note> notwithſtanding he was ſlain in battle, by enemies in open hoſtility againſt him; which might have mitigated their grief: How inexcuſable would the neglect of a ſorrowful reſentment of murder of our Engliſh Joſiah be; ſeeing he was not ſlain in the <hi>heat of War</hi> (which would have excuſed <hi>a tanto,</hi> though not <hi>a toto</hi>) but butchered in cold <hi>Blood,</hi> in <hi>time of peace by his own Subjects,</hi> or at leaſt thoſe that ought to have been ſuch. It was the ſaying of our Martyred Sovereign himſelf, <hi>That it is more honourable for a King to be invaded</hi> &amp; <hi>almoſt deſtroyed by Forreigners then to be diſpiſed at home.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 55.12, 13, 14.</note> Had it been an enemy I could have borne: But it was thou O Man, my friend, and mine acquaintance. <hi>The Dagger of Brutus peirced Caeſars heart, more then any of the reſt, which he intimated to him in his laſt words,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. And <hi>Scipio</hi> was wont to ſay, that he had rather <hi>Hannibal</hi> ſhould <hi>ear</hi> his <hi>Heart</hi> with <hi>ſalt, then Lelius his friend</hi> offer him the <hi>least</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kindneſſe. How did David weep over the Hearſe of Abner, being
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:96629:8"/>perfidiouſly murthered by <hi>Joab.</hi> He commanded the people to rent their cloathes,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 3.31.32, 33, 35.</note> and gird them with ſackcloth, and mourn be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Abner.</hi> And King <hi>David</hi> himſelf followed the Bier, and lift up his voice and wept at the grave of <hi>Abner,</hi> ſaying, <hi>Died Abner as a fool Dieth;</hi> and all the people wept again over him. And David would not taſt bread, or ought elſe, till the Sun was down, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by all Iſrael underſtood that day, that it was not of the King to ſlay
<hi>Abner</hi> the Son of <hi>Ner.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Did David a <hi>King</hi> ſo much lament the murder of <hi>Abner</hi> his <hi>ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject?</hi> How much more ſhould we <hi>Subjects</hi> lament the murder of our <hi>Sovereign,</hi> that all the world may know, that it was not of us to ſlay <hi>Charles</hi> King of England.</p>
            <p>That <hi>funeral oration</hi> and <hi>mournful Elegy,</hi> which David pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced for the death of <hi>Saul,</hi> with a little variation, will ſerve for our occaſion.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>2</hi> Sa. <hi>1.17.</hi> to the end</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>England</hi> laments with this lamentation over King Charles the firſt, <hi>ver.</hi> 17. The beauty of <hi>England</hi> is ſlain upon thy high places: how is the mighty faln!
<hi>ver.</hi> 19? Tell it not in Gath, publiſh it not in Askelon: leaſt the daughters of the Philiſtines rejoice; leaſt the daughters of the uncircumciſed triumph, <hi>ver.</hi> 20. How was the crown, yea blood of the mighty vilely caſt away; the blood <hi>Charles</hi> of as if he had not been the Anointed of the Lord, <hi>ver.</hi> 21.</p>
            <p>Ye daughters of England weep for <hi>Charles</hi> who cloathed you with Scarlet, with other delights; who put on ornaments of Gold upon your apparel, <hi>ver.</hi> 24. O <hi>Charles</hi> thou waſt ſlain at the Gate of thy Palace! <hi>ver.</hi> 25. we are diſtreſſed for thee, Oh King Charles, very pleaſant haſt thou been unto us: thy love to us was wonderful, paſſing the love of Women, <hi>ver.</hi> 26.</p>
            <p>How did the mighty Prince fall and the Royal Crown pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh!</p>
            <p>That the horrid nature of this cruel Regicide may be more ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly repreſented unto you, as an argument for humiliation. Conſider, Firſt, the Act it ſelf. Secondly, the manner of its commiſſion. Thirdly, The Object thereof. Fourthly, the Authors. Fifthly, The effects and conſequents.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Conſider the <hi>nature of the act it ſelf:</hi> It was not only con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt, impriſonment, but murther.</p>
            <p>The Superlative love of <hi>Abraham</hi> unto God was amplified, in that he was willing not only to chaſtiſe, Diſinherit, or baniſh his Son <hi>Iſaack;</hi> but alſo to kill him, by cutting his throat, ripping open
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:96629:8"/>his bowels, and burning his quarters on the Alta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>: ſo it is, on the contrary the high aggravation of the high Treaſon, for which we mourn this day, that it was not <hi>terminated</hi> in ſome <hi>ſmal affronts;</hi> but proceeded to the effuſion of <hi>the Royal blood of his Sacred Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Murder <hi>Purpoſed,</hi> though not <hi>perpetrated</hi> is of an infinite guilt. Sin <hi>conceived in the heart</hi> is damnable, though it never come to the birth, or be brought forth. Was it not a curſed and Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolical deſign in <hi>Faux,</hi> and the reſt of the
<hi>Gunpouder-Traytors, at one blow, to blow up King Prince and Nobles;</hi> notwithſtanding it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved <hi>Abortive?</hi> how villanous then were thoſe bloody conſultati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and reſolutions, which came to <hi>Maturity,</hi> and ripened unto the execution of the Lords Anointed!</p>
            <p n="3">3. It was a <hi>voluminous,</hi> and <hi>bigbellied</hi> ſin; a ſin in <hi>folio,</hi> which containeth a great litter of other ſins, in the belly of it. Ingratitude envy, malice, covetouſneſſe, ambition, rebellion, perjury, Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, blaſphemy were the <hi>bitter ingredients,</hi> whereof this <hi>confection of porſon</hi> was compounded.</p>
            <p n="4">4. It was a ſin that admitted of no reparation. An <hi>impriſoned</hi> Prince might have been <hi>ſet at liberty, a dethroned</hi> Prince <hi>inthroned</hi> againe; but a
<hi>murdered</hi> Prince <hi>cannot be revived.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, Conſider the manner how the Death of our Royal Sovereign was effected. It was no
<hi>caſual</hi> or, <hi>involuntary act,</hi> no <hi>chance-medly,</hi> nor
<hi>man-ſlaughter:</hi> but <hi>wilful murther.</hi> How <hi>studi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly</hi> and
<hi>Deliberately</hi> was it acted! with what <hi>Impudence</hi> and <hi>ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice,</hi> with what
<hi>boaſting</hi> and <hi>triumph,</hi> with what <hi>impenitency</hi> and
<hi>Remorſleſneſſe,</hi> and with what a <hi>fixed reſolution</hi> againſt all admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and ſupplications was it committed! Murders of Kings in former ages being done
<hi>privately,</hi> were <hi>modeſtly</hi> acted in compariſon of this.</p>
            <p>It was the aggravation, as of <hi>Abſaloms</hi> inceſt,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Sa.</hi>
16.22.</note> that he ſpread a tent on the houſe top, and went into his Fathers Concubines in the ſight of all <hi>Iſrael.</hi> So of our <hi>King-ſlayers</hi> treaſon, that they
<hi>built a Scaffold before the Royal Palace,</hi> and adventured on the <hi>Decol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation</hi> of the father of the Nation, in the <hi>face of the Sun,</hi> before <hi>thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands</hi> of ſpectators in the moſt <hi>populous City</hi> of <hi>London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, Conſider the object of this cruelty, or the ſubject whereon it was acted. Not a
<hi>private perſon,</hi> but a <hi>King,</hi> whoſe perſon is ſacred, by the <hi>Law</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> of <hi>Nature,</hi> and of <hi>Nations:</hi> yea not only a King, but a
<hi>Chriſtian,</hi> a <hi>Proteſtant</hi> King. <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> &amp; his Apoſtles acknowledged ſubjection <hi>unto,</hi> &amp; the primitive Chriſtians prayed
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:96629:9"/>
               <hi>for heathen Em<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>rors.</hi> The Jews were commanded to ſeek the peace of the <hi>King of Babylon,</hi> to whom they were captives. <hi>Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicai</hi> diſcovered the treaſon plotted againſt the life of
<hi>Ahaſuerus,</hi> by his two Chamberlaines.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſth.</hi> 3.21, 22,
23.</note> If the lives of Pagan Emperors, and <hi>bloedy Butchers of the Church,</hi> were precious in the eyes of the primitive Chriſtians; then certainly the murder of a <hi>Gracious King,</hi> and <hi>Nurſing Father</hi> ought to be unfainedly lamented by all that name the name of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As the Husbandmen ſlew not only the ſervants,<note place="margin">Math. <hi>21.</hi>
               </note> but the <hi>Son</hi> of the Lord of the vineyard; and the Jews not only the <hi>Apostles</hi> and
<hi>Prophets,</hi> but alſo the <hi>father of the Prophets, Jeſus Chriſt</hi> himſelf; So our <hi>Engliſh Cannibals</hi> drank not only the blood of the <hi>Nobles</hi> and
<hi>Peeres</hi> of the Realm, the <hi>Divines</hi> and <hi>Miniſters</hi> of the Church, but alſo the <hi>Royal blood</hi> of their ſacted <hi>Sovereign.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. The <hi>Authors</hi> and <hi>Actors</hi> of this cruell <hi>Maſſacre,</hi> and bloo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy <hi>Tragedy</hi> were <hi>ſubjects, ſworn</hi> ſubjects, that had taken the oaths of
<hi>Allegiance, and Supremacie, Profeſſed Chriſtians,</hi> yea, <hi>Proteſtants.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It had been enough for <hi>Forreigners, Heathens, Popiſh Inquiſitors, Recuſants, Jeſuites A Ravilliack, a Faux,</hi> to have attempted ſuch a deviliſh wickedneſs: But for perſons obliged by the laws of <hi>Nature,</hi> of <hi>Nations,</hi> of <hi>Humanity,</hi> and
<hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> by their own <hi>Oathes, Proteſtations, Covenants</hi> to defend the authority, and life of their Sovereign, yet <hi>unnaturally, inhumanely, barbarouſly, impiouſly, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidiouſly,</hi> to take away his life; What a <hi>volume</hi> of wickedneſſe was it?</p>
            <p n="5">5. Conſider the <hi>Malignant</hi> influences and effects hereof, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference to the
<hi>Royal Family, England,</hi> our <hi>Neighbour Nations,</hi> and <hi>Religion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, The <hi>Death-day</hi> of our preſent dread Sovereignes Royal Father, was the birth-day of <hi>Woe</hi> and miſery, to himſelf, and all the <hi>Royall Family:</hi> Even as when the <hi>Root</hi> is digged out of the Earth all the <hi>branches wither.</hi> So barbarous a butchery, of ſo glorious a Father, could not but work exceſſive ſorrow in all their royal breſts, by reaſon of natural <hi>Sympathy,</hi> and filial-affection. How were they exiled from the inheritance of their Father, their native ſoil, and the imbraces of their loving ſubjects, to wander about, like <hi>David</hi> in the Wilderneſſe! <hi>Quis talia fando temperet a lachrimis!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>Englands happineſſe</hi> being <hi>imbarked,</hi> and bound up in the life of its King, <hi>(as Jacobs in the life of his Son Joſeph)</hi> it was <hi>ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrackt</hi> together with him. The <hi>Eclipſe</hi> of our <hi>Royall Sun benighted.</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:96629:9"/>the Kingdom with all its glories, as <hi>Phineas his wife</hi> named her child
<hi>Ichabod,</hi> ſaying the glory is departed front <hi>Iſrael;</hi> becauſe the Ark of God was taken: So might we have wrote <hi>Ichabod</hi> on all our injoyments, ſaying the glory is
<hi>departed from England,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Anointed of the Lord was taken from us; which like the opening of flood-gates cauſed a <hi>Deluge,</hi> and <hi>inundation</hi> of calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties to flow upon <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, What an evil example did this <hi>Engliſh</hi> Regicide yeild to neighbour Nations, to incourage them to riſe up and cut the throats of their Princes: yoa the memory of ſuch a villany is enough to infect <hi>poſterity,</hi> and to <hi>poyſon the generations to come with King-killing principles.</hi> Sins, the <hi>more contagious</hi> they are, the <hi>more hainous,</hi> as the Plague is the worſt of all diſeaſes, becauſe moſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectious. Thus
<hi>Memucan</hi> aggravateth the diſobedience of <hi>Queen Vasthi</hi> to her husband; becauſe ſhe had done wrong, <hi>not only to the Kings Perſon, but alſo to all the Princes</hi> and people of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces of King <hi>Ahaſuerus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſth.</hi> 1.16, 17,
18.</note> by giving an evil example unto all the Ladies and Women of <hi>Media</hi> and
<hi>Perſia,</hi> to deſpiſe and diſobey their husbands.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, What ſcandal hath been brought unto the <hi>Proteſtant Religion,</hi> as if the principles thereof did juſtifie the murder of kings. It hath <hi>groaned</hi> and <hi>travelled in pain</hi> until now, under that reproach which hath been caſt upon it, by reaſon of that pre onded zeal for God, which was made uſe of to colour, cloake, maske, and diſguiſe the murder of the King: who therefore might have ſaid as <hi>Henry the 7th Emperor of Germany</hi> did, when he was <hi>poyſoned in the Euchariſt,</hi> and felt the operation thereof, <hi>Calix vitae, Calix mortis, the cup of life is made the cup of death to me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Abſaloms Rebellion</hi> againſt his Father,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15.7, 10.
1 <hi>Kin.</hi> 21.</note> under pretence of a <hi>vow</hi> to be paid at <hi>Hebron. Jezebles proclaiming a faſt,</hi> for the more plauſible murder of <hi>Naboth.</hi> And <hi>Jehu's extirpation of Ahabs po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity, his competitors</hi> for the Kingdom, and <hi>Baals prieſts</hi> their <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bettors, pretendedly</hi> out of zeal for God; but
<hi>intentionally</hi> for his own eſtabliſhment on the Throne, ſeem to be the originall and
<hi>Proto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>type</hi> from whence thoſe blaſphemous and <hi>Hypocriticall tranſactions,</hi> in order to the murder of K. <hi>Charles</hi> were tranſcribed: for this likewiſe was
<hi>hatched</hi> under the <hi>warme wings,</hi> and <hi>ſwadled</hi> up in the <hi>mantle of abuſed Religion,</hi> yea, never did a child more <hi>reſemble his Father,</hi> then the actions of Engliſh <hi>Abſalom's, Jehu's, Jezebels,</hi> do the actions of thoſe <hi>Jewiſh hypocrites.</hi> They anſwer one another, <hi>as face anſwereth face in a glaſſe. Uladiſlaus King of Hunga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> having agreed on a ceſſation of Ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e; with the <hi>Turks,</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:96629:10"/>did notwithſtanding, upon an advantagious opportunity, aſſault them: The
<hi>Turks</hi> perceiving the battle to goe againſt them, cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out, O <hi>Jeſus, Jeſus! wilt thou permit ſuch perjured perſons to call themſelves Chriſtians?</hi> Whereupon the battle turned, and the Chriſtians were vanquiſhed. Likewiſe an <hi>Indian</hi> rejected Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiani y, and <hi>vilified Heaven,</hi> becauſe he heard the <hi>Spaniards</hi> did goe th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> her; whoſe cruelty rendred both their
<hi>perſons</hi> and <hi>Religion</hi> abhorred.</p>
            <p>What offence do even <hi>Turks,</hi> and <hi>Infidels</hi> take at the abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble practiſes of profeſſed Chriſtians, and how great a wound is given to religion hereby! As the ſight of
<hi>Aſahels Dead body</hi> ſtopt the march of <hi>Joabs ſouldiers:</hi> ſo the groſſe failings of profeſſors of Religion, cauſe ſome to ſtagger at, and others to retreat back from the prfe ſſion it ſelf.</p>
            <p>Wherefore take up weeping, and wailing, ye inhabitants of <hi>England,</hi> for that the holy and reverent name of God, pure and undefiled <hi>Religion</hi> hath been ſo much
<hi>blaſphemed,</hi> abuſed, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted to, and made a <hi>Stalking-horſe for</hi> the vile luſts and bloo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy deſignes of ambitious men; eſpecially in that God-<hi>diſhonouring, Goſpel-diſgracing, Religion-reproaching</hi> ſin of
<hi>regicide,</hi> that was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted amongſt us. I have read a dreadful ſtory, concerning a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of <hi>Stage-players,</hi> whilſt ſome of them were perſonating and acting the part of the <hi>Devil,</hi> the real <hi>Devil</hi> came in amongſt them, and drove them all away.
<hi>If the Devil diſdaineth to be brought upon the ſtage in a mockery, much more doth the Jealous</hi> God.</p>
            <p>There are two obſtructions, which, if not removed, may poſſibly abate the edge of your ſorrow, for the murther of <hi>King Charles;</hi> to wit, the long diſtance of time ſince which it was committed, And your perſwaſion of your innocency and freedom from the guilt thereof.</p>
            <p>For the firſt, <hi>The old Age</hi> of this murder ſhould be ſo far from antiquating the ſenſe thereof, or <hi>blunting</hi> the edge of your humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, that it ſhould rather
<hi>accelerate</hi> and increaſe it; for, the time paſt is enough, yea too much, for the nation to have retained the guilt of that Royal blood: Now it is high time to awake out of ſleep, and by a <hi>National</hi> repentance, to teſtifie an abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of the Treaſon; leaſt that judgement, which hath been hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto ſuſpended ſhould now be executed. God may
<hi>reprieve,</hi> when he doth not pardon a Nation: forbearance is no acquir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance. The Lord avenged the ſlaughter of the <hi>Gibeonites</hi> by <hi>Saul</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:96629:10"/>many years after the commiſſion thereof,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Sam.</hi>
21.1, 2. 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 35.25.</note> even in the Reign of <hi>David,</hi> with three years famine on Iſrael. Thoſe words, <hi>They ſpake of Joſiah</hi> in their lamentations unto
<hi>this day,</hi> do denote the conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuation of their ſorrow for him a long time after his death.</p>
            <p>Secondly, notwithſtanding, this ſin was contrived and actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally committed but by
<hi>few,</hi> and deteſted by the <hi>majority</hi> of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: yet I fear moſſt of the people of <hi>England</hi> have contracted the guilt thereof, upon theſe two grounds.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Becauſe they did not riſe up as one man, with an unani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous reſolution to reſcue their captived <hi>Sovereign</hi> out of the hands of thoſe roaring Lyons, and deſtroying Bears, which devou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red him: even as all Iſrael did to reſcue their <hi>beloved Jonathan,</hi> who cried out, <hi>ſhall Jonathan Dy? God forbid, as the Lord li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth, there ſhall not one hair of his head fall to the ground.</hi> This ſhould have been <hi>Englands</hi> voice, reſolution, and indeavour in behalf of their King, <hi>Cauſae non impedientes</hi> are numbered by <hi>Phyloſophers</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong moral <hi>efficient cauſes. Qui non prohibet, quod poteſt, jubet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. For defect of ſufficient <hi>humiliation. General inſenſibleneſſe</hi> ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders a ſin national, as well as <hi>common practice.</hi> I doubt <hi>Eng.</hi> ſorrow hath not been proportionable to the degree of <hi>Englands</hi> ſin. <hi>Sins</hi> that have been buried a long time in the grave of <hi>oblivion,</hi> may <hi>revive</hi> in their puniſhment. It was a pious deſire of a <hi>Reverend Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine,</hi> that a <hi>National faſt</hi> might be ſolemnly obſerved for the inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent blood of <hi>Holy Martyrs ſhed in</hi> Queen Maryes
<hi>Reign.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Achan</hi> only took of the accurſed thing, and yet it is ſaid,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Joſh.</hi> 7. <hi>ve.</hi> 6. &amp; 11.</note> 
               <hi>all Iſrael ſinned,</hi> and committed a treſpaſſe before the Lord, And all Iſrael ſuffered for the ſin of
<hi>Achan.</hi> Beloved the murder of <hi>King Charles</hi> may be an <hi>Achan</hi> in
<hi>England,</hi> to bring down the curſe of God upon it; unleſſe we acquit our ſelves by ſerious hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliation from the guilt thereof.</p>
            <p>All the righteous blood ſhed upon the earth, from the blood of Righteous <hi>Abel,</hi> unto the blood of <hi>Zacharias</hi> the ſon of <hi>Barachi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as, ſlain</hi> between the Temple and the Altar, is charged by <hi>Chriſt</hi> on the Phariſees. If the blood of <hi>Abel</hi> might juſtly be imputed to a people, that never had finger in it, 4000. <hi>years</hi> after it was ſhed; Much more may that innocent <hi>Royal blood</hi> which was ſhed, but 12 <hi>years ſince,</hi> be a <hi>Moth</hi> and a <hi>Canker</hi> to <hi>England;</hi> unleſſe we of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer up the Sacrifice of a broken and contrite heart unto the Lord. Wherefore, let us hang our harps upon the Willowes, and mourn when we remember King <hi>Charles</hi> the firſt, as the
<hi>Iſraelites</hi> ſate down by the rivers of <hi>Babylon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſa.</hi> 137.1, 2.</note> and <hi>wept</hi> when they remembred
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:96629:11"/>
               <hi>Zion.</hi> Let us breath out our ſorrow in the words of the Prophet
<hi>Jeremiahs Lamentations</hi> for the captivity of <hi>Zedechiah, The breath of our noſtrels, the anointed of the Lord was taken in their pits,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lam.</hi> 4.20.</note> of whom we ſaid, <hi>under the ſhadow of his wings we ſhall live and flouriſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Naturaliſts</hi> relate that the hard <hi>Adamant</hi> it ſelf, being <hi>bathed</hi> in the <hi>blood</hi> of a <hi>Goat,</hi> will be <hi>ſoftned</hi> and <hi>diſſolved:</hi> So were your hearts of a <hi>Rock-like, Flint-like, Adamantine</hi> nature, yet methinks being bathed in the <hi>blood of a King,</hi> they ſhould be diſſolved into tears of Godly ſorrow.</p>
            <p>O <hi>curſed Ax!</hi> that at one blow cut off the <hi>head of three King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes,</hi> and left them as <hi>Dead carkaſſes.</hi> O <hi>Glorious Prince!</hi> with what <hi>Kiſſes</hi> of
<hi>diſſimulation</hi> did <hi>Engliſh Judaſses</hi> betray thee! How was thy ſacred perſon, in imitation of our bleſſed <hi>Saviour,</hi> (who was crowned with Thorns, ſpit on, ſcourged, buffeted, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viled) expoſed to ſcorn and ignomy! How were thy <hi>Nobles</hi> and <hi>Peeres</hi> who were wont to attend thy royal Perſon, <hi>Exchanged</hi> for
<hi>Jaylors,</hi> thy <hi>Palace</hi> for a <hi>priſon,</hi> thy <hi>Throne</hi> for a ſcaffold and a <hi>Block!</hi> Did not the adverſaries of King <hi>Charles</hi> cry out, <hi>Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Execution,</hi> as the Jews againſt <hi>Chriſt, Crucifie him, Crucifie him;</hi> Finally his royal head was cut off with a cruel Ax; as the bleſſed heart of Chriſt was pierced with a cruel Spear.</p>
            <p>Was not this the moſt monſtrous and barbarous act, the moſt bloody tragedy of all tragedies, that ever were acted, ſince the cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifying of the Son of God, for a company of abjects not only to abuſe, vilifie their Sovereign with the opprobrious names of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lefactor, Traytor, and the like; but alſo to arraigne, condemn and execute him. Had they touched only his royall robes, it had been a violation of their duty, but they deveſted themſelves of chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, Loyalty, yea Humanity it ſelf, and cut off his royall head. <hi>Hear O Heavens, give Ear O Earth, gather blackneſſe and be aſtoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed!</hi> for a great evil hath been committed amongſt us. <hi>O Sun in thy race throughout the whole world, even the moſt barbarous corners thereof, didſt thou ever take notice of a more inhumane murder?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>O that we had ſome <hi>Jeremiah</hi> with <hi>Eyes</hi> as <hi>water,</hi> and an
<hi>head</hi> as <hi>a fountain of teares,</hi> to lament the death, and <hi>ſing the obſequies</hi> of our Mattyred King, yea to write a book of lamentations for him, as he did for the captivity of King <hi>Zedechiah.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Again, from <hi>Davide</hi> humiliation for, and intention in ſmiting <hi>Sauls</hi> Robe, compared together: Obſerve,
<q>That a good intention doth not juſtify an evil,<note place="margin">Obſerv.</note> and diſloyal action.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:96629:11"/> 
               <hi>Davids</hi> deſigne was to procure a teſtimony of his innocency; that
<hi>Saul</hi> beholding the skirt of his robe in <hi>Davids</hi> hand, might be fully convinced, that <hi>David</hi> had no deſign againſt his life: then which he could never have propoſed a better end to himſelf, next to the glory of God, and ſalvation of his ſoul; and yet being
<hi>conſcious</hi> of <hi>ataxy</hi> in his action, his heart ſmites him for it. An
<hi>Act</hi> for the matter and ſubſtance thereof <hi>Lawfull,</hi> may for <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect</hi> of a right <hi>modification,</hi> &amp; <hi>a good end,</hi> be but <hi>ſplendidum peccatum:</hi> but it is impoſſible that an act <hi>materially evil,</hi> ſhould be rectified by the
<hi>beſt end</hi> aimed at therein. <hi>A garment</hi> of <hi>good cloath</hi> may be marred in the <hi>making:</hi> but a <hi>good garment</hi> can never be made of <hi>bad cloath.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>prevention</hi> of evil, doth not juſtify the <hi>commiſſion</hi> of evil, in order thereunto. <hi>Lots deſire</hi> to prevent <hi>Sodomy,</hi> did not <hi>autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rize</hi> him to permit <hi>Adultery,</hi> by proſtituting his daughters to the luſt of the Sodomites.
<hi>Herod</hi> was not to be excuſed, when he ruſhed on the <hi>Rock of murther</hi> in beheading <hi>John the Baptiſt,</hi> at the requeſt of his <hi>Dancing minion,</hi> to avoid the <hi>ſands of perjury.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 14.10.</note> Neither doth the attainment of the greateſt <hi>good,</hi> change the nature of an evil action. The preſervation of <hi>Lots poſterity</hi> did not excuſe his <hi>Daughters inceſt;</hi> nor the procurement of the bleſſing, <hi>Rebe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kahs treachery,</hi> and <hi>Jacobs</hi> lying. The <hi>Lord</hi> ſmote <hi>Uzzah</hi> that he died, for touching the Ark; though out of an in ention to keep it from falling, when the Oxen ſtumbled.<note place="margin">1 <hi>Chro.</hi> 13.9.10. <hi>Joh.</hi>
16.2. <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.</note> Chriſt tells his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, that the time ſhould come, that ſome ſhould think, <hi>they did God good ſervice</hi> in killing them. <hi>Paul</hi> during his Phariſaiſm perſecuted the Church of God, <hi>out of zeal.</hi> Men may give their bodies to be <hi>burned,</hi> and yet die not as Martyrs, but as <hi>malefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors.</hi> An Heretick may ſeal his hereſy with his <hi>Blood;</hi> as <hi>Serve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus at Geneva.</hi> I Doubt not but many
<hi>Mahumetans</hi> would <hi>Dy,</hi> ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then renounce their religion. The glory of
<hi>Martyrdom</hi> requires <hi>a juſt</hi> and <hi>righteous cauſe</hi> to be ſuffered for, as well as a <hi>good</hi> intent in them that ſuffer. Martial law excuſeth not a Captain excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding his commiſſion; notwithſtanding he did it out of a good intention, and with good ſucceſſe. Subjects ſhould not be inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious to their Prince, either for the ſake of Religion, or ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill Liberty. <hi>Davids</hi> intention ſmiting <hi>Sauls</hi> Skirt, was Honourable, yet the Act it ſelf is Condemned by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf.</p>
            <p>I come now to the Second part of the Text.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:96629:12"/> 
               <hi>Davids Loyal deteſtation of cutting off the Royall head of the Lords Anointed, manifeſted in his excellent Oration.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Part.
<hi>II.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. The Occaſion whereof, firſt preſents it ſelf to our conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which was two-fold; Firſt, the fit Opportunity; Secondly, The great <hi>Importunity</hi> he had to ſlay
<hi>Saul:</hi> from whence note theſe two fundamentall principles of loyalty.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That the fitteſt opportunity, wherein to offer violence to a Prince, is to be rejected.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That the greateſt importunity thereunto, is to be reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Obſ. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>That the fitteſt opportunity, wherein to offer violence to a King is to be rejected.</hi> Opportunity is the
<hi>Touchſtone</hi> of Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>David</hi> might have effected the death of <hi>Saul</hi> with the greateſt
<hi>certainty,</hi> and with the greateſt ſecurity.</p>
            <p n="1">1.<note place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 24.4</note> 
               <hi>With the greateſt certainty. David</hi> and his men had ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compaſſed <hi>Saul</hi> in the Cave, that his men cryed out unto him, behold the day, of which the Lord ſaid unto thee, I will deliver thine enemy into thine hand, that thou mayeſt do to him, as ſhall ſeem good unto thee. <hi>Saul</hi> being aſleep in the Trench, <hi>Abiſhai</hi> ſaid unto <hi>David,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi>
26.8.</note> let me ſmite him, I pray thee with the ſpear, even to the Earth at once, and I will not ſmite him the ſecond time. <hi>David</hi> finding <hi>Saul</hi> in the Cave, might have ſmote off his Head, as well as the <hi>Skirt</hi> of his <hi>Robe;</hi> and turned the
<hi>Cave</hi> into his <hi>Grave.</hi> And finding him aſleep in the Trench, he might have took away, inſtead of the <hi>Cruiſe of water from his Bolſter,</hi> ſo much <hi>blood from his Heart,</hi> and made it his laſt ſleep; courting him with that Complement, wherewith a Captain once courted his Souldier, whom he found aſleep on the watch, when he thruſt his Sword into his bowels, ſaying, <hi>Dead I found thee, and dead I leave thee.</hi> But this was the
<hi>Crown</hi> and <hi>Glory</hi> of <hi>Davids</hi> loyalty, that he was
<hi>Opportunity-proof.</hi> As the <hi>Salamander</hi> remaineth <hi>unſcorched</hi> in the
<hi>Fire;</hi> and as a man in a Peſt-houſe eſcapeth the infection of the Plague, ſo
<hi>David</hi> preſerves his loyal breaſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainted with theſe temptations; inſtead of improving opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyes, for the acting of murther, he converts them into <hi>Trophyes</hi> of his fidelity; had <hi>David</hi> abſtained from an attempt on <hi>Sauls</hi> life, only while the
<hi>Succeſſe</hi> was <hi>Dubious,</hi> it would have been an argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his <hi>Policy;</hi> But to forbear it, when he had ſuch an <hi>oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune ſeaſon,</hi> at one blow, to make this
<hi>Royal Lyon,</hi> that was ſo <hi>ram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pant,</hi> not only <hi>couchant,</hi> but alſo a
<hi>Dead Carkaſſe,</hi> was a <hi>Monument</hi> of his Loyalty.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:96629:12"/>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>With the greateſt ſecurity.</hi> Had <hi>David</hi> been the Object of the Peoples Envy, a deſire of ſelf-preſervation was enough, to reſtrain him from the Murder of
<hi>Saul,</hi> leſt the Noiſe of ſuch a Fact ſhould have given an Alarm to the People, to riſe up as one man, to avenge the bloud of their King, and like Lions robbed of their Whelps, to tear him into pieces as a deſtroyer of their Countrey. But <hi>David</hi> was ſo far from the danger of being expoſed to the rage and fury of the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> that he was even their Idol: Inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much, that <hi>Saul</hi> being ſlain, he might have expected their
<hi>Accla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations,</hi> rather than <hi>Exclamations;</hi> their Congratulations for his Safety, rather than their condoling of <hi>Sauls</hi> death.</p>
            <p>Peruſe the Hiſtory, and it will appear, what great intereſt he had in the Affections, and what great applauſe from the mouths of the Children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> 1 Sam. 18.5. <hi>He behaved himſelf ſo wiſely, that he was accepted of all the people, and of Sauls Servants.</hi> And <hi>v.</hi> 6, 7. VVith Tabrets and with Harps they ſang, <hi>Saul hath ſlain his thouſands, and David his ten thouſands.</hi> How willingly did the men of
<hi>Judah</hi> anoint him King after <hi>Sauls</hi> death, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 3.4.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Deſervedly</hi> was <hi>David</hi> thus eſteemed of his Countrey-men: For never did any
<hi>gallant Romans,</hi> not <hi>Regulus</hi> or <hi>Cato</hi> themſelves merit better of their Countrey, than <hi>David</hi> of his.</p>
            <p>Now how different was Loyal <hi>David</hi> from the mind of his Son <hi>Abſalom?</hi> The Son by fair Speeches and courteous behaviour ſtole away the hearts of the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> and then employed them in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15.2. to 7. But the Father not only ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtained from all <hi>ſubtil Inſinuations</hi> and horrid <hi>Calumniations</hi> of <hi>Sauls</hi> Perſon and Government; but when his Deſerts (like the Sun) drew all eyes and affections unto him, yet diſdained to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert his, popular intereſt and favour to any rebellious De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign.</p>
            <p>This Self-denial condemneth our <hi>Engliſh Abſaloms,</hi> who by <hi>Machivilian diſſimulation,</hi> and ſlandering the Footſteps of the Lords Anointed, ſought to render his <hi>Perſon odious,</hi> and his <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtauration impoſſible; themſelves amiable,</hi> and their <hi>Uſurped Power impregnable.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Likewiſe it admoniſheth all Perſons of <hi>Renown</hi> and <hi>Intereſt</hi> in their Countrey, to employ themſelves in <hi>extinguiſhing,</hi> rather than <hi>fomenting</hi> that
<hi>Turbulency</hi> which is a <hi>Chronical diſeaſe</hi> in the Vulgar.</p>
            <p>Now <hi>Davids</hi> abhorrence of Revenge, when he might ſo <hi>certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> and ſo
<hi>ſecurely</hi> have diſpatched his Enemy, ſets ſuch an <hi>Empha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis</hi>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:96629:13"/>on his <hi>Loyalty,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 24.17, 18,
19.</note> that it ſtruck <hi>Saul</hi> himſelf into an <hi>admiration</hi> and
<hi>adoration</hi> of it.</p>
            <p>It is nothing for a <hi>Beggar,</hi> who hath not ſufficient for <hi>neceſſity,</hi> to abſtain from <hi>ſuperſluity;</hi> but to fit at a Rulers Table, ſwimming with all manner of Dainties, and to put a Knife to the throat, to be temperate with <hi>Timothy,</hi> among luxurious <hi>Aſians,</hi> enhaunceth the worth of Tempetance.</p>
            <p>As it was the Glory of <hi>Joſeph</hi> that he rejected a fair opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and great importunity to commit adultery, <hi>Gen.</hi> 39.7, 8, 9. As it was the Honour of <hi>Joſeph</hi> afterward, in <hi>Pharoah</hi>'s Court, of <hi>Obadiah,</hi> in <hi>Ahabs,</hi> of <hi>Daniel,</hi> in <hi>Nebuchadnezzars,</hi> of <hi>Nehemiah,</hi> when Cup-bearer to <hi>Artaxerxes,</hi> of
<hi>Lot</hi> in <hi>Sodom,</hi> and of the Saints in <hi>Nero</hi>'s Houſe, a monſter of men,
<hi>Phil.</hi> 4.22. that they retained their Piety, notwithſtanding the manifold Temptations and opportunities unto ſin wherewith they were aſſaulted; ſo like a Diamond in a Ring, it ſets a great price on <hi>Davids</hi> Loyalty, that at the <hi>Cave</hi> he did not violate it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Not to ſeek</hi> an opportunity for revenge, is honourable; but to <hi>reject it,</hi> when <hi>offered,</hi> is <hi>double honour.</hi> Many are not diſloyal, becauſe they
<hi>cannot,</hi> rather then becauſe they <hi>would not.</hi> As <hi>Tul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> ſaith of the
<hi>Catalinarians, aliis Facultas defuit, aliis Occaſio, vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntas profectò nemini.</hi> As the Tap to the Veſſel, and the Spark to dry Tinder, as the fire to benummed fingers, and Aquavitae to a fainting perſon, ſuch is a <hi>fit opportunity</hi> to a <hi>diſloyal heart.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Many who have been good Subjects, have proved bad Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors; and many who have been tolerable Cardinals, when ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced to the Papal Chair, have proved <hi>Luxurious Sodomites, Aegyptian Magicians, devouring Abaddons,</hi> and <hi>Incurable Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonians;</hi> ſo difficult is it to withſtand the Force of an inviting op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity unto ſin.</p>
            <p>Wherefore <hi>Job,</hi> Ch. 31. V. 1. made a Covenant with his eyes, that he would not look upon a woman, leſt he ſhould luſt after her. And <hi>Solomon</hi> admoniſheth us, not to look on the Wine, when it is <hi>red,</hi> when it <hi>giveth its colour in the Cup,</hi> and <hi>moveth it ſelf aright;</hi> leſt by the <hi>pleaſant colour,</hi> we ſhould be allured to an
<hi>exceſſive uſe thereof,</hi> Prov. 23.31. But Vertues, how much the more
<hi>difficult,</hi> are ſo much the more <hi>honourable.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It was an <hi>Impeachment</hi> of <hi>Jacobs</hi> Fraternal affection to <hi>Eſau,</hi> that he took the opportunity of his hunger, to buy him out of the <hi>Prerogatives</hi> of
<hi>Primogeniture,</hi> Gen. 25.31, 33.</p>
            <p>Though in other cales, <hi>David</hi> was eaſily overcome by Tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:96629:13"/>(the ſight of a naked <hi>Bathſhoha</hi> provoked him to violate his Chaſtity; and the unkindneſs of <hi>Nabal,</hi> to meditate revenge and Murder) yet ſo great an Influence had the ſacred Office of a King on his heart, that the ſight of <hi>Saul</hi> in a Cave, could not wound his Loyalty. As the skill of a Pilot is tried in a ſtorm, and the valour of a Souldier in a Battel; ſo an opportunity of ſin is the proof of vertue. It is frequent with men to exclaim, againſt a Fact, before they are in a capacity to commit it, and yet after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward to become notoriouſly guilty of that, againſt which they ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed.</p>
            <p>With what indignation did <hi>Hazael</hi> anſwer the Prophet <hi>Eliſha,</hi> telling him that he ſhould rip up women with Child, and daſh out the Brains of Children, 2 <hi>Kings</hi>
8.13. <hi>But what is thy Servant a Dog, that I ſhould do this great thing?</hi> But when he became King of <hi>Syria,</hi> the Propheſie of <hi>Eliſha</hi> was fulfilled;
<hi>Magiſtratus indicat virum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The greateſt Importunity to offer violence to a King, is to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Obſerv. 2.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Davids</hi> Souldiers did importunately ſolicite him to ſlay <hi>Saul,</hi> 1
<hi>Sam.</hi> 24.4, 10. <hi>Some bade me kill thee.</hi> 2 Sam. 26.8. <hi>Abiſha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſaid, now let me ſmite him, I pray thee, with the ſpear unto the earth;</hi> Theſe words do virtually include ſuch like
<hi>Expoſtulations</hi> as theſe;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>O David,</hi> Thou haſt for a long time been hunted as a <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tridge in the Mountains;</hi> we thy ſtedfaſt Friends, even in <hi>advenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> have hazarded our Lives and deareſt blood for thy defence: VVherefore embrace this opportunity, and make it the death of
<hi>Saul,</hi> and our own Miſeries; <hi>betray as</hi> not by thy <hi>vain ſcruples,</hi> and
<hi>fooliſh lenity,</hi> into the hands of an <hi>implacable,</hi> and deceitful Adverſary.</p>
            <p>VVhat ſtrong <hi>Obligations</hi> had <hi>Davids</hi> Souldiers laid on him to
<hi>gratiſte</hi> their requeſt, by the denial whereof he might fear, left they ſhould
<hi>revolt</hi> from him, and <hi>upbraid</hi> him, with preferring his <hi>enemies</hi> before his
<hi>Friends;</hi> as <hi>Joab</hi> did, when he mourned for the death of <hi>Abſalom,</hi> 2 Sam.
19.5, 6. <hi>Thou haſt ſhamed this day the faces of all thy ſervants, which have ſaved thy life, and the lives of thy Wives and Concubines, in that thou loveſt thine enemies, and hateſt thy frituds: For thou haſt declared this day, that thou regardeſt nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Prinors nor fervants; for I perceive, that if Abſalom had lived, and all we had died this day, it would have pleaſed thee well.</hi> Beſides, what <hi>plauſible Reaſons for,</hi> and what ſeeming
<hi>neceſſity of</hi> the death
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:96629:14"/>of <hi>Saul,</hi> might have been ſuggeſted to <hi>David?</hi> But he looking more to <hi>preſent duty,</hi> than <hi>future danger,</hi> choſe rather to hazard all his concernments, then to condiſcend to a ſinful act, though cloaked with ſuch ſpecious pretences, as might have drowned the harſh ſound of Murder. <hi>Importunity</hi> is no
<hi>Apology</hi> for <hi>Impiety:</hi> VVere this Rule obſerved, it would ſave many Thieves and Traytors from the Gallows. How frequently do <hi>malefactors</hi> at the time of execution complain againſt their evil Companions, who ſeduced them?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Adams</hi> Plea, <hi>The woman gave me, and I did eat,</hi> Gen. 3.12. Nor <hi>Eves, The Serpent beguiled me, and I did eat,</hi> Gen. 3.13. were not accepted by God, for their taſting the Forbidden Fruit.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Moſes</hi> would not acquit <hi>Aaron</hi> from the guilt of Idolatry, when he made the Golden Calf, though he pleaded the importunity of the people, <hi>Exod.</hi> 32.22. <hi>Thou knoweſt this people is ſet on miſchief, and they ſaid unto me make us gods. Samuel</hi> urgeth on <hi>Saul</hi> his ſin, in ſparing <hi>Agag,</hi> and the beſt of the ſpoil, until he confeſſed, <hi>I have ſinned, I have tranſgreſſed, becauſe I feared the people, and obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed their voice,</hi> 1 Sam. 15.24. An evil action is to be <hi>fathered</hi> on the
<hi>Actor,</hi> and not to be tranſlated to the <hi>Tempter.</hi> Temptations
<hi>reſisted,</hi> are the Tempters ſins, and not ours; but if <hi>embraced,</hi> they become our ſins as well as the Tempters. The <hi>fire</hi> of temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation would do no hurt, without the dry <hi>Tinder</hi> of our own luſts; For, <hi>where there is no wood, the fire goeth out,</hi> Prov. 26.20. But as Coals are to burning Coals, ſo is a <hi>vitiated nature</hi> to <hi>corrupt ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gestions.</hi> Solicitations have no <hi>conſtraining</hi> or <hi>compulſive power over the will,</hi> but only an <hi>enticing and alluring vertue;</hi> they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not <hi>infuſe</hi> any <hi>vicious quality</hi> into the mind, but only ſtir up that Luſt which is in it already; they work not in a <hi>phyſical,</hi> but in a <hi>moral</hi> way. There can be no
<hi>Adultereſs</hi> without an <hi>Adulterer.</hi> VVere there not a <hi>formative vertue</hi> in the womb of the corrupt heart, giving life unto <hi>ſinful injections,</hi> they would prove
<hi>abortive births;</hi> though an <hi>Enticer</hi> may be ſaid to be the <hi>Father begetting,</hi> yet the <hi>corrupt heart</hi> is the <hi>mother conceiving</hi> and <hi>bringing forth</hi> the <hi>Baſtard-brood</hi> of ſin.</p>
            <p>Should a man rob or ſtab you, and plead that he was <hi>tempted</hi> to it, would you be ſatisfied with ſuch an excuſe? Importunity, is no cloak for diſloyalty; foraſmuch as the
<hi>counter-perſwaſions</hi> of God in his Word from it are <hi>greater</hi> than mens ſolicitations unto it: Now (as <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>John</hi> anſwered the Jewiſh Rulers)
<hi>Whether is
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:96629:14"/>it right in the ſight of God, to hearken unto men more than unto God, judge ye.</hi> The violent <hi>Clamours</hi> of the <hi>Jews</hi> againſt Chriſt,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 4.19.</note> 
               <hi>Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifie him, Crucifie him,</hi> did not acquit
<hi>Pilate</hi> from the guilt of his bloud; but according to their <hi>imprecation</hi> of judgment on, and <hi>execration</hi> of themſelves, it hath been on the heads of them and their children, this 1600 years. The <hi>Petitioners</hi> which were <hi>ſuborned</hi> againſt
<hi>King Charles,</hi> like <hi>Jezabels falſe Witneſſes</hi> againſt <hi>Naboth,</hi> did not diſcharge the <hi>Actors</hi> of that <hi>Fatal Tragedy,</hi> from the guilt of his <hi>Royal Blood.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All the plauſible Remonſtances, ſpecious pretences, and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phiſtical Pleas, which our late Juglers raiſed, to delude the inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicious Vulgar, <hi>vaniſh</hi> before this evident teſtimony, deduced from <hi>Davids</hi> Loyalty, notwithſtanding the diſloyal clamours of his Souldiers; even as <hi>Dagon fell down</hi> before the <hi>Ark,</hi> and as the <hi>Miſts</hi> and <hi>Vapours</hi> in the Air are <hi>chaſed</hi> away by the glorious <hi>beams</hi> of the
<hi>ariſing Sun.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now poſſibly ſome who have <hi>raſed</hi> out all Principles of <hi>Religion</hi> and
<hi>Reaſon</hi> out of their minds, may arraign <hi>David</hi> for a perſon of an
<hi>abject</hi> and <hi>ignoble ſpirit,</hi> and condemn him for <hi>Folly</hi> and
<hi>puſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lanimity,</hi> becauſe he made not <hi>Ambition</hi> and <hi>ſelf-advancement</hi> his <hi>Card</hi> and <hi>Compaſs,</hi> whereby to <hi>steer</hi> his courſe; but neglected ſo fair an opportunity to acquire a Kingdom. This Enditement will appear to be no <hi>Billa vera,</hi> but a <hi>Forgery;</hi> and <hi>Davids Loyalty</hi> to be no <hi>Impeachment</hi> either of his <hi>Prudence</hi> or <hi>Magnanimity,</hi> if we review the precedent Hiſtory, wherein are recorded moſt undoub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted proofs of both. Let that Subjects <hi>Valour</hi> be accounted
<hi>Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolical fury,</hi> and his <hi>wiſdom diabolical Subtilty,</hi> that <hi>claſheth</hi> and <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfereth</hi> with his <hi>Allegiance,</hi> and is <hi>inverted</hi> againſt his
<hi>Soveraign.</hi> Thus much in reference to the <hi>Occaſion</hi> of <hi>Davids</hi> Oration.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Now followeth the <hi>Orator: He,</hi> i. e. <hi>David,</hi> ſaid unto his men;
<list>
                  <item>1. <hi>David a Subject.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>David a Captain of Souldiers.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>David a Subject:</hi> From whence note,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That Subjects ought not to be contented with perſonal Loyalty,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Obſerv.</note> 
               <hi>but ſhould endeavour to Loyalize others.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As <hi>Light,</hi> ſo <hi>Loyalty,</hi> is not to be <hi>hid under a Buſhel.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi>
5.15.</note> Loyalty is of a <hi>diffuſive nature,</hi> it will not be <hi>engroſsed</hi> and
<hi>monopolized,</hi> it will not be <hi>put into a Napkin,</hi> or <hi>locked up</hi> in
<hi>private breasts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>David</hi> would not <hi>impriſon,</hi> his Loyalty in his own breaſt, but cauſeth it-to flame forth in a Loyal Oration, that it might kindle
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:96629:15"/>the like <hi>Sacred fire</hi> in the breaſts of others.</p>
            <p>Piety toward God, and Loyalty toward our King, ſhould be of a like nature. It is the property of <hi>Grace</hi> to be <hi>commuica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive.</hi>
               <note place="margin">John <hi>1.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>Andrew</hi> having found the Meſſiah, calleth <hi>Simon,</hi> and <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lip, Nathanael. Moſes</hi> could even wiſh his Name were blotted out of the Book of Life, and <hi>Paul</hi> himſelf, accurſed from Chriſt, for the ſake of the <hi>Iſraelites.</hi> So Loyalty is of a <hi>ſpreading</hi> and <hi>aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milating</hi> nature; like fire, that converts the Fuel into its own ſubſtance; like Leaven that <hi>leaveneth</hi> the whole Lump; and like the
<hi>Philoſophers ſtone,</hi> that turneth what it toucheth into <hi>Gold.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>With what <hi>Marks</hi> of <hi>Infamy</hi> do ſuch deſerve to be <hi>branded,</hi> who have
<hi>run counter</hi> hereunto, not only by <hi>perſonal diſloyalty,</hi> but alſo by indefatigable induſtry to <hi>poyſon others</hi> with Principles of Sediti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. The Holy Ghoſt
<hi>ſtigmatizeth</hi> thoſe, who incited the <hi>Jews</hi> to rebel againſt the King of
<hi>Babylon,</hi> with the Names of <hi>Diviners, Enchanters</hi> and <hi>Sorcerers.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jer.</hi> 29.9.</note> O, that all who have endeavoured to <hi>propagate Treaſon</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> by <hi>ſeditious Pamphlets,</hi> would deal with their
<hi>Libels</hi> as the <hi>Sorcerers</hi> did with their <hi>conjuring Books;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 19.19.</note> 
               <hi>they brought them together, and burned them before all men, and count<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Price, and found it fifty thouſand Pieces of ſilver.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2.<note place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 22.2.</note> Conſider <hi>David in a military capacity, as Captain of Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers.</hi> 400 people gathered themſelves to him, and he became Captain over them. <hi>Generals of Armies</hi> ſhould perſwade their Souldiers not only to be
<hi>valiant</hi> againſt their <hi>Enemies,</hi> but alſo <hi>faithful</hi> to their
<hi>King.</hi> The great <hi>dignity conferred</hi> on them, the great <hi>truſt repoſed</hi> in them, their <hi>Authority over,</hi> and <hi>Intereſt in</hi> their Souldiers, do all require this duty from them. Beſides, Souldiers are uſually very <hi>reſpectful</hi> to the
<hi>Perſons, obſequious</hi> to the <hi>Commands, obſervant</hi> of the <hi>directions,</hi> and apt to <hi>imitate</hi> the <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples</hi> of their <hi>Leaders.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It was ſaid of <hi>Naaman</hi> the <hi>Syrian,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Kin.</hi>
5.1.</note> that he was a great man, and honourable, <hi>but</hi> a Leper. To praiſe a man with a
<hi>but,</hi> is <hi>but</hi> to diſpraiſe him.</p>
            <p>It is a wound and diſhonour never to be wiped off from the Names of ſome Generals, that they were Famous and Valiant Warriours, <hi>but</hi> they inverted their Arms againſt their Soveraigns
<hi>A Commendation with this Diſcretive,</hi> but, <hi>is a diminutive Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It gives an <hi>Accent</hi> to the <hi>Renown</hi> of <hi>Joab,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2.
<hi>Sam.</hi> 12.</note> that he would not <hi>build</hi> up his <hi>own</hi> Glory, out of the
<hi>Ruines</hi> of his <hi>Kings.</hi> After he had almoſt taken <hi>Rabbah, he ſent Meſengers to David, ſaying Gome
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:96629:15"/>and encamp againſt it, leſt I take the City, and it be called by my Name.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The memory of our late Military Officers will ſtink in the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrils of all Loyal Subjects, becauſe they <hi>debauched</hi> the minds of their Souldiers with ſeditious Principles,
<hi>inſtigated</hi> them unto Rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and by ſubtil Inſinuations <hi>inthroned</hi> themſelves in their Affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, in order to the <hi>dethroning</hi> of their <hi>Soveraign.</hi> But let it be <hi>recorded</hi> for the perpetual <hi>Renown</hi> of our <hi>Famous</hi> and
<hi>Heroical Engliſh General,</hi> that he trode in the Footſteps of <hi>David,</hi> that he took up the Cudgels againſt our <hi>rampant</hi> Enemies, who were ſo <hi>drunk</hi> with
<hi>Succeſs,</hi> that they <hi>defied</hi> all <hi>Antagoniſts,</hi> as <hi>Goliah</hi> did
<hi>David;</hi> and that he employed his Arms for effecting the happy Reſtauration of our Dread Soveraign, King <hi>Charles</hi> the Second, to his Throne and Kingdom. Wherefore let his
<hi>Name</hi> be <hi>preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous</hi> unto the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> as the Names of <hi>Gideon, Barak, Samſon, Jepthah,</hi> and the reſt of thoſe <hi>Worthies</hi> of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> were unto that Nation, for being Inſtruments of their deliverance out of the hands of <hi>Midianites, Moabites, Ammonites</hi> and <hi>Philiſtines.</hi> Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this <hi>Magnanimous Hero's tutelar Sword,</hi> next unto His <hi>Royal Majeſties tutelar Scepter,</hi> (the principal efficiency, and the <hi>Glory</hi> of, being <hi>reſerved for,</hi> and <hi>aſcribed unto</hi> the
<hi>Great God</hi>) <hi>England</hi> is <hi>indebted</hi> for all its Happineſs.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Third Member obſerved in the <hi>diſſection</hi> of this Verſe is
<hi>Davids Auditors:</hi> He ſaid to his <hi>men, i. e.</hi> Souldiers, being a p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ck of hungry and bankrupt perſons.<note place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 22.2</note> 
               <hi>Every one that was in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs, in debt, and diſcontented, gathered themſelves to him.</hi> Theſe mens wants might provoke them to offer violence to <hi>Saul,</hi> that they might be inriched with his Spoiles, and have his Kingdom for a Prey. Therefore <hi>David</hi> darteth forth this Loyal Oration, (that as cold water caſt into a Pot, ſtayeth the boyling thereof) it might allay the violent Aeſtuations of their Paſſions.</p>
            <p>Souldiers of all men, have moſt need of Loyal Inſtruction, that it may be an
<hi>Antidote</hi> againſt the <hi>Poyſon</hi> of the Temptations ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing from a <hi>military Employment.</hi> All is fiſh that cometh to net with Sword-men, they are apt to put no difference between the <hi>Princes Robes</hi> and the <hi>Peaſants Ruſſet;</hi> they are ſo accuſtomed to Inſtruments and Acts of Cruelty, that <hi>immanity</hi> becomes <hi>natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral to,</hi> and <hi>habituated in</hi> them. <hi>Inter Arma ſilent Leges.</hi> The <hi>ſounding Trumpet, the roaring Cannon,</hi> and the <hi>ratling Spear,</hi> (like the noiſe of the
<hi>Aegyptian Cataracts,</hi> which (as it is reported) maketh the adjacent inhabitants almoſt deaf) hindereth the <hi>voice
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:96629:16"/>of the Law</hi> from being heard; and the <hi>Sword</hi> will be made uſe of, for the <hi>deciſion</hi> of Controverſies,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Kings</hi> 3.24, 25.</note> as it was by <hi>Solomon</hi> in another manner. As Fire in the <hi>Chimney</hi> is neceſſary and profitable, but on the <hi>Houſe-top</hi> dangerous and pernicious; ſo though a
<hi>Militia</hi> be ſometimes neceſſary for the <hi>defence</hi> of a Nation, and the
<hi>offence</hi> of its Enemies; yet if the military <hi>inſolence</hi> of the Souldiers be not
<hi>allayed</hi> by godly and Loyal Inſtruction, it will be poyſon in ſtead of
<hi>Phyſick</hi> to the <hi>Body Politick.</hi> If the hearts of Souldiers be not
<hi>ſeaſoned</hi> with Loyalty, they will grow ſo inſolent, and be ſo <hi>Pinacle high</hi> in Pride, that they will endewour to turn their <hi>Belts</hi> into <hi>Robes,</hi> their
<hi>Head-pieces</hi> into <hi>Crowns,</hi> and advance their <hi>ſwords</hi> above the
<hi>Scepter</hi> of their Soveraign, as <hi>England</hi> hath found by ſad Experience.</p>
            <p>Wherefore <hi>John the Baptiſt catechiſeth</hi> the Souldiers that came unto him,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi>
3.14.</note> after this manner; <hi>Do violence to no man, accuſe no man falſly, and be content with your wages.</hi> And <hi>David</hi> in the Text, teacheth his Souldiers to cauſe their Swords to do <hi>Homage</hi> to <hi>Sauls</hi> Scepter, (as the <hi>Sheaves</hi> of
<hi>Joſephs</hi> Brethren made <hi>Obeyſance</hi> to his) in a <hi>Lecture</hi> of Loyalty; which leads me to the Fourth Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The <hi>Oration it ſelf,</hi> wherein is expreſſed;</p>
            <p n="1">1. A <hi>Vehement Deteſtation: The Lord forbid.</hi> This Expreſſion denoteth the greateſt <hi>Abhorrence</hi> of an Act. When the Ten <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarchs</hi> would manifeſt their Indignation againſt ſtealing <hi>Joſephs</hi> Silver Cup,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi>
44.7.</note> they ſay, <hi>The Lord forbid that thy Servants ſhould do this thing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Iſraelites</hi> proteſting againſt the death of their beloved
<hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nathan,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 14.45. <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.14.6. <hi>Rom.</hi>
2.</note> cry out, <hi>Shall Jonathan die, who hath wrought ſo great ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation in Iſrael? God forbid. Is there unrighteouſneſs with God? God forbid. Shall we continue in ſin that Grace may abound? God forbid. Paul's</hi> deteſtation of <hi>Blasphemy,</hi> and <hi>Davids</hi> of the <hi>mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> of his <hi>King,</hi> are ſet forth by like expreſſions, to ſhew the <hi>af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finity</hi> between theſe two ſins.</p>
            <p>There ought to be not only a <hi>reluctancy</hi> againſt, an <hi>averſeneſs</hi> from, a
<hi>forbearance</hi> of, and a <hi>reſolution</hi> againſt injuriouſneſs to the Sacred perſons of Princes, but alſo a fixed reſolution joyned with the greateſt <hi>Antipathy</hi> againſt it, an <hi>Abolition</hi> of diſloyal, and an <hi>introduction</hi> of Loyal
<hi>Principles,</hi> to denominate Subjects <hi>eminently Loyal.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Many, who have <hi>Rebellious hearts,</hi> yet ſtretch forth no <hi>Rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous hands,</hi> but 'tis for want of a <hi>temptation,</hi> rather than of an <hi>incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation</hi> thereunto.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:96629:16"/> Methinks I hear the hearts and tongues of all faithful Subjects,
<hi>ecchoing</hi> forth a reply to all Suggeſtors of Treaſon, in ſuch a <hi>Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect</hi> as
<hi>Balaam</hi> did to <hi>Balak,</hi> deſiring him to curſe <hi>Iſrael, If Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lak would give me his houſe-full of Gold and ſilver, I cannot go beyond the Command of the Lord, to do this thing;</hi> and as <hi>Hazael</hi> to <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſha, Is thy Servant a Dog, that he ſhould do this great thing?</hi> I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not conſent unto the <hi>Effuſion of Royal Blood,</hi> unleſs I ſhould <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce Religion, Reaſon</hi> and <hi>Humanity</hi> it ſelf, and
<hi>Nebuchadnez<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zar-like,</hi> be <hi>transformed</hi> into ſome <hi>Bruit Beaſt,</hi> ſome
<hi>Tyger, Wolf, Bear</hi> or <hi>Lion:</hi> Yea, unleſs I could <hi>exchange</hi> my
<hi>humane,</hi> for a <hi>Diabolical</hi> Nature; becauſe it is ſuch a barbarous and prodigious wickedneſs, which ſhall be demonſtrated under the next Head.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The <hi>Act Deteſted,</hi> which is expreſſed with an <hi>Emphaſis,</hi> in theſe words, <hi>that I ſhould do this thing, i. e.</hi> this <hi>Horrid,</hi> this
<hi>abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable</hi> thing, <hi>to ſtretch forth my hand againſt the Lords Anointed.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Kin.</hi> 8.13.</note> It ſounds as high as the like Expreſſion of
<hi>Hazael;</hi> —<hi>That I ſhould do this great thing,</hi> i. e. this <hi>Inhumane Villany,</hi> to rip up wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men with child, and to daſh out the Brains of Children.
<hi>Stretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing forth the hand</hi> againſt a Perſon, is an uſual <hi>Periphraſis of mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> in Scripture-Dialect. <hi>David</hi> ſchooling the <hi>Amalekite,</hi> for ſlaying
<hi>Saul,</hi> ſaith, <hi>How waſt thou not afraid to ſtretch forth thy hand againſt the Lords Anointed?</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 1.14.</note>
            </p>
            <p>That the <hi>Murder of a King</hi> may appear in its <hi>bloody colours,</hi> conſider it under the <hi>Notion,</hi> 1. Of <hi>Homicide.</hi> 2. Of <hi>Regicide.</hi> Which is capable of a triple Aggravation; being,
<list>
                  <item>1. <hi>Paricide.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>Sacricide.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. <hi>Deicide.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Of <hi>Homicide.</hi> I take not this Word in a <hi>Juridical</hi> and
<hi>Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renſical</hi> ſenſe, as it is <hi>diſtinguiſhed</hi> from <hi>Wilful Murder;</hi> but, as in its <hi>genuine</hi> ſignification, it imports the Murder of a <hi>man,</hi> as a
<hi>rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable Creature,</hi> and <hi>abſtracted</hi> from any <hi>extrinſecal denomination,</hi> ariſing from <hi>ſuperadded</hi> Honour.</p>
            <p>This <hi>Scarlet</hi> and <hi>Crimſon</hi> ſin being <hi>died</hi> in <hi>Blood,</hi> was one of the firſt Crimes againſt which God enacted a <hi>penal Law,</hi> and for which he allotted a <hi>Capital puniſhment.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 9.6. <hi>Pro.</hi> 28.13.
<hi>Pſal.</hi> 35.23.</note> He that <hi>ſheddeth mans Blood,</hi> by man ſhall his bloud be ſhed; for in the Image of God made he man. He that ſheddeth the <hi>Bloud</hi> of <hi>any</hi> Perſon, haſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to the Grave, let no man hinder him. <hi>Bloody</hi> and deceitful men ſhall not live out half their daies.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Murder</hi> is ſo contrary to the <hi>Light of Nature,</hi> and ſo deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:96629:17"/>to <hi>Humane Society,</hi> that the <hi>Barbarians</hi> ſeeing a Viper on
<hi>Pauls</hi> hand, ſaid, no doubt, this man is a Murderer, whom, though he hath eſcaped the Sea, yet divine vengeance will not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer him to live.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi>
28.4.</note> It were eaſin to recite many <hi>Dreadful Examples</hi> of Gods judgments inflicted on Murderers.</p>
            <p>How often have Murders <hi>concealed</hi> for many years, been at length even <hi>miraculouſly revealed?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Murderers have ſomtimes been <hi>ſtruck dead</hi> by the immediate hand of God from Heaven; and ſomtimes been their <hi>own executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners,</hi> by hanging, ſtabbing, or drowning themſelves. And as God rained fire and brimſtone (Hell out of Heaven) on <hi>Sodom</hi> and
<hi>Gomorrah,</hi> ſo hath he often cauſed ſome <hi>ſparks of Hell-fire</hi> to fly into the Conſciences of Murderers, and tormented them in a kind of Hell upon Earth, with a continual ſenſe of Blood-guilti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. Bloud lieth <hi>heavy</hi> on the <hi>Stomack,</hi> but <hi>more heavy</hi> on the <hi>Conſcience.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. If <hi>Homicide</hi> be ſuch a capital Crime, much more is <hi>Regicide.</hi> If
<hi>that</hi> like <hi>Cain.</hi> ſhall be avenged <hi>ſeven fold, this</hi> like
<hi>Lamech,</hi> ſhall be avenged <hi>ſeventy and ſeven fold.</hi> Nothing but the bloud, of
<hi>Zebah</hi> and <hi>Zalmunna</hi> would pacifie <hi>Gideon,</hi> becauſe they ſlew his brethren,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iudges</hi> 8.18.19. 2 <hi>Kin.</hi> 9.31.</note> though they only
<hi>reſembled</hi> the <hi>Sons</hi> of a <hi>King.</hi> Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment hath alwaies purſued
<hi>King-killers. Had Zimri peace who ſlew his Maſter?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The bowels of the Earth became the Habitation of <hi>Korah</hi> and his <hi>Complices,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Num.</hi> 19. 2 <hi>Sa.</hi> 20.22.</note> for conſpiring againſt <hi>Moſes, King in Jeſurun.</hi> The Head of Rebellious <hi>Sheba</hi> became a juſt <hi>Sacrifice</hi> to pacifie the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of <hi>Joab.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Life</hi> of a <hi>King</hi> is <hi>equivalent</hi> to the Lives of <hi>ten thouſand</hi> Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects. The King ſaid,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 18.2, 3.</note> I will ſurely go forth with you my ſelf: But the people anſwered, thou ſhalt not go forth; for if we flee away, they will not care for us, neither if half of us die, will they care for us; but <hi>thou</hi> art <hi>worth</hi> ten thouſand of <hi>us;</hi> therefore now it is better that thou ſuccour us out of the City.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sacred Hiſtory</hi> is full of the Noble Examples of Loyal Subjects, who have been even
<hi>prodigal</hi> of their <hi>Lives</hi> for the ſake of their So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign.</p>
            <p>What <hi>Volunteers</hi> were the People of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> in <hi>jeoparding</hi> their Lives for the ſake of <hi>David,</hi> in <hi>Abſaloms,</hi> and <hi>Sheba</hi>'s Rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons? You may find a <hi>Catalogue</hi> of ſuch Heroes in 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 23.<note place="margin">2
<hi>Sam.</hi> 20.2.</note> Amongſt whom, <hi>Abiſhai</hi> deſerves an <hi>eminent Character</hi> for his Loyalty: When <hi>Iſhbi-benob</hi> thought to have ſlain <hi>David,</hi> he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:96629:17"/>into a Combate with him, though a <hi>Giant,</hi> a ſecond <hi>Goliah,</hi> and ſlew him. Yea, how ready was he to adventure his Life,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Sa.</hi>
21.17.</note> that he might wound the <hi>heart</hi> of <hi>Shime<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> becauſe he wounded the <hi>good name</hi> of his
<hi>Soveraign.</hi> The <hi>Life</hi> of <hi>David</hi> was ſo <hi>precious</hi> in the eyes of all his Subjects, that they <hi>ſware</hi> unto him, ſaying,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Sam.</hi>
16.9.</note> Thou ſhalt no more <hi>go forth</hi> with us to battel, leſt thou <hi>quench</hi> the <hi>light</hi> of <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Sa.</hi> 21.17.</note>
            </p>
            <p>How ſharply doth <hi>David</hi> rebuke <hi>Abner,</hi> for <hi>Life-guarding Saul</hi> no better. <hi>As the Lord liveth, ye are worthy to dye,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 26.15,
16.</note> 
               <hi>becauſe you have not kept your Maſter, the Lords Anointed.</hi> He that is not
<hi>with</hi> me, is <hi>against</hi> me, ſaith Chriſt: So he that <hi>defendeth not</hi> a Prince, <hi>deſtroyeth</hi> him. Chriſt alledgeth the duty of Subjects, to defend their Soveraign, as a Principle ingrafted in the hearts of all men. If my Kingdom were of this world, then would my Subjects fight for me,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>John</hi> 18.36.</note> that I ſhould not be delivered into the hands of the Jews. Chriſtianity engageth us to lay down our lives for the ſake of Chriſt: So Loyalty obligeth us to adventure them for the ſafety of our King. Wherefore how do ſuch <hi>degenerate</hi> from the nature, not only of <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> but alſo of <hi>men,</hi> who are ſo impious, and ſo impudent, as to attempt the
<hi>Deſtruction of Kings;</hi> for the <hi>Preſervation</hi> of whoſe Perſons, they ought to <hi>ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice</hi> their own <hi>Bloud.</hi> That the Murder of a King may appear to be a deteſtable impiety, conſider it;</p>
            <p n="1">1. As <hi>Paricide.</hi> Kings are ſtiled <hi>Nurſing Fathers,</hi> and Queens
<hi>Nurſing Mothers.</hi> The ſame <hi>Compellation David</hi> uſed to <hi>Saul:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 49.23. 1 <hi>Sa.</hi> 24.11.</note> 
               <hi>My Father,</hi> ſee the skirt of thy Robe in my hand</p>
            <p>Not only <hi>Natural, Oeconomical</hi> and <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Fathers,</hi> but alſo
<hi>Political Fathers</hi> are included in the <hi>Fifth Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If <hi>Fratricide</hi> cauſed <hi>Cain</hi> to be a Vagabond and a Fugitive on the Earth, and
<hi>Abſalom</hi> to be <hi>baniſhed</hi> out of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> how great <hi>guilt</hi> is contracted, and how great <hi>puniſhment</hi> deſerved by <hi>Paricide?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is ſuch an <hi>unnatural Act,</hi> that the Ancient <hi>Romans</hi> would enact <hi>no Law</hi> againſt it; becauſe they thought none would be ſo <hi>barbarous,</hi> as to commit it. It is a <hi>complicated</hi> ſin, for hereby a man deſtroyeth him that begat him, that loved and educated him, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So that to kill a King, who is <hi>Pater Patriae,</hi> is by Analogy, as if a man ſhould cut the throat of his Father that begat him, and rip up the bowels of his Mother that conceived him. What be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:96629:18"/>of Trayterous <hi>Abſalom,</hi> who ſought the Life and Kingdom of his Natural, and Political Father? Was he not deſervedly hanged between the boughs of an Oak? VVere not <hi>Joabs</hi> darts fit <hi>Chyrurgical Inſtruments,</hi> by a juſt kind of
<hi>Phlebotomy,</hi> to let out his <hi>unnatural blood?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Regicide is <hi>Sacricide.</hi> As it is <hi>Sacriledge</hi> to <hi>prophane holy</hi> and <hi>conſecrated things,</hi> ſo it is <hi>Sacricide</hi> to murder the <hi>Anointed</hi> and <hi>Sacred Perſons</hi> of Kings.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Regicide is (with reverence be it ſpoken) <hi>Deicide; a kind of God-Murder.</hi> Methinks, now I hear ſome Melancholy illite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Sectarian, exclaiming againſt me, as the High Prieſt againſt Chriſt.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.65.</note> This man hath ſpoken
<hi>Blasphemy;</hi> for God is not like man, that he ſhould be ſubject unto death.</p>
            <p>That I may <hi>vindicate</hi> my Aſſertion from this hainous Charge; know, that it is to be underſtood, not <hi>Properly,</hi> but <hi>Analogical<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</hi> It is ſpoken <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and muſt be interpreted <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>God forbid that I ſhould aſſert any <hi>poſſibility</hi> of <hi>Mutation</hi> in the
<hi>Divine Eſſence,</hi> which is altogether <hi>impaſſible.</hi> Our Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs cannot profit him, nor our Sins hurt him.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Job.</hi> 22.2, 3. <hi>Iob.</hi>
35.6, 7, 8.</note> It was the <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie</hi> of the <hi>Anthropomorphites,</hi> that they aſcribed unto God <hi>humane Members,</hi> and an <hi>Organical Body;</hi> becauſe the Scripture attribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth Eyes, Ears, Hands, and Bowels unto him; thus they trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed the incorruptible God into an Image made like unto cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptible man.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi>
1.23.</note> Whereas ſuch Speeches do only denote, that what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever Perfection accreweth unto the body, by the uſe of ſuch Members, is in an eminent and infinite degree found in Gods thus
<hi>Eyes and Ears</hi> denote Gods <hi>Omniſcience, Hands</hi> his <hi>Omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potence; Bowels</hi> his infinite <hi>Mercy</hi> and Compaſſion. Now with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out bordering on this Hereſie, the Murdering of ſupream Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates may be called God-murder, though not actually and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly, yet <hi>interpretatively:</hi> The Lord accounts it as ſuch.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Jews,</hi> though they murdered only the Body of Chriſt, yet ſhed the <hi>Blood of God:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 20.28.</note> becauſe there is a <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> a
<hi>Communication of Properties,</hi> ariſing from the <hi>hypoſtatical Union</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Divine and Humane Natures of Chriſt, whereby what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever doth agree to one Nature, may be ſpoken of the whole Perſon.</p>
            <p>Chriſt accounteth the Perſecution of his <hi>Members,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi>
9.4. <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.6. <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.45. <hi>Luke</hi> 10.16.</note> to be a Perſecution of
<hi>himſelf;</hi> by reaſon of the <hi>Myſtical Union</hi> between them.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:96629:18"/> In like manner, God <hi>appropriates</hi> the Murder and Contempt of Magiſtrates <hi>unto himſelf;</hi> becauſe they receive their <hi>Commiſſions</hi> from him, ſtand in his ſtead, <hi>repreſent</hi> his Perſon, are called by his <hi>Name,</hi> and are his <hi>Deputies</hi> and <hi>Vicegerents.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.30.
<hi>Iſa.</hi> 63.10. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 43.24. <hi>Amos</hi> 2.13. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 6.9.
<hi>Ezek.</hi> 16.43. 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 8.7.</note>
            </p>
            <p>As the Lord is ſaid to be grieved, vexed, wearied, and made to ſerve, preſſed as a Cart with ſheaves, and broken, and fretted with mens Iniquities and Tranſgreſſions; ſo to be rejected and deſpiſed, in the rejection and contempt of Magiſtrates. Saith the Lord to
<hi>Samuel,</hi> they have not rejected thee, but they have rejected <hi>me,</hi> that <hi>I</hi> ſhould not reign over them.</p>
            <p>Affronts offered to <hi>Ambaſſadors</hi> redound to the diſhonour of the <hi>King</hi> that ſent them. <hi>David</hi> furiouſly revenged the abuſe of his <hi>Ambaſſadors,</hi> when the <hi>Ammonites ſhaved off their Beards,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 10.</note>
               <hi>and cut off their garments in the middle.</hi> Kings are the extraordinary Ambaſſadors, which the great Jehovah hath ſent into the world; he will plead their cauſe, and avenge their quarrels againſt all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellious Subjects. Wherefore let all men refrain from offering violence to Kings, leſt (as <hi>Gamaliel</hi> ſpake in another caſe) they be found to <hi>fight againſt God.</hi> And let us lament this day,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 5.39.</note> the horrid, monſtrous, barbarous, inhumane, abominable and dete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtable Murder of King
<hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt, becauſe it was repugnant and contrary to <hi>Humanity,</hi> as it was <hi>Homicide;</hi> to <hi>Nature,</hi> as <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricide;</hi> to <hi>Loyalty,</hi> as
<hi>Regicide;</hi> to <hi>Piety,</hi> as <hi>Deicide:</hi> becauſe it was at once the Murder of
<hi>a man, a King, a Father, a God:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſ.</hi> 82.6.</note> I have ſaid ye are <hi>gods, i. e. gods</hi> in <hi>Office,</hi> though not in <hi>Eſſence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Conſider the Perſon deteſting this Act; God forbid that <hi>I,</hi> (i. e.
<hi>David</hi>) ſhould do this thing. And <hi>Davids</hi> heart ſmote him.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>V.</hi> 5.</note> There are many Circumſtances relating to the Perſon of
<hi>David,</hi> that do very much <hi>ampliſie</hi> his Loyalty.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. He was Injured.</item>
               <item>2. Anointed.</item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1. Injured <hi>David</hi> mourns for cutting off the skirt, and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horreth cutting off the Head of <hi>Saul:</hi> From whence note;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That Injuries received by Subjects from their Soveraign,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Obſerv.</note> 
               <hi>are not to be accounted a ſufficient Charter, to abſolve and diſcharge them from their Allegiance; nor a ſufficient Patent, to authorize and commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate them, to exerciſe revenge, rebellion and violence againſt him; but ought to be ſwallowed down and paſſed by, with a meek and patient ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit:</hi> Or thus;</p>
            <p>Subjects oppreſſed by their King, by reaſon of his falſe and groundleſs ſuſpitions concerning them, ought to be the more ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licitous
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:96629:19"/>to clear up their innocency and vindicate their Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>David</hi> deſerved as well of his King and Countrey, as ever any <hi>Roman Generals</hi> riding in triumph through the ſtreets of <hi>Rome,</hi> with Captives bound to their Chariot wheels, did of theirs.</item>
               <item>2. He received not only an <hi>inadequate</hi> and inſufficient <hi>reward,</hi> but
<hi>no</hi> reward; yea, he was not only <hi>non-rewarded,</hi> but <hi>evilly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated. Saul</hi> ſought after his Life.</item>
               <item>3. Yet his carriage is ſo meek and Heroical, that it ſcarce ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits of an Hyperbole or Parallel. For never was a Subjects In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegrity more <hi>groundleſly ſuſpected,</hi> his
<hi>Morits</hi> more <hi>unſutably reward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</hi> his <hi>Injuries</hi> more <hi>wrongfully received,</hi> and yet his <hi>behaviour</hi> more <hi>gallantly Loyal,</hi> than <hi>Davids.</hi> He revenged the Injures received from <hi>Saul,</hi> by ſtudying, to approve himſelf innocent, by redoubled courage againſt the <hi>Philistines.</hi> As <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, where
<hi>ſin</hi> did abound, <hi>Grace</hi> did much more abound; ſo <hi>Davids Loyalty</hi> did exceed <hi>Sauls tyranny. Saul</hi> would have ſmote <hi>David</hi> to the wall with a
<hi>Javelin,</hi> though he could not; but <hi>David,</hi> though he <hi>could</hi> have ſmote
<hi>Saul</hi> to the Cave with a <hi>Sword,</hi> yet <hi>would not.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>As the Oak is more ſtrongly rooted by the winds, and the fire burneth moſt fiercely in winter, by reaſon of the Antiperiſtaſis of cold; ſo <hi>Davids</hi> undeſerved Perſecution was rather like Oyl, to increaſe, than water to extinguiſh that Loyal Fire, that was in his breaſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Davids</hi> deſign in cutting off <hi>Sauls</hi> skirt, was no other, than (as <hi>Goliahs ſword</hi> was laid up behind the <hi>Ephod,</hi> to be a <hi>Monument</hi> of <hi>Davids victory</hi> over him) to obtain a Trophy and Monument of his Loyalty.<note place="margin">1
<hi>Sam.</hi> 24.9, 10.</note> Wherefore heareſt thou mens words, ſaying, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold
<hi>David</hi> ſeeketh thy hurt? Behold, this day thine eyes have ſeen, how that the Lord had delivered thee into my hands in the Cave, and I ſaid, I will not ſtretch forth my hand againſt my Lord, for he is the Lords Anointed: Moreover he ſaid, yea, ſee the skirt of thy Robe in my hand: For in that I cut off the skirt of thy Robe, and did not kill thee, know thou, and ſee, that there is neither evil nor tranſgreſſion in my hands; and I have not ſinned againſt thee, yet thou hunteſt my ſoul to take it.</p>
            <p>If you conſider <hi>Davids</hi> conſequent contrition of ſpirit, for but the ſhadow of diſloyalty, in ſmiting <hi>Sauls</hi> garment, and his vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment antipathy againſt deſtroying his Life, it will appear, that God hath ſtamped ſuch inviolable authority on all Kings, as well the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:96629:19"/>evil, as the good, that they are exempted from the Laſhes of their Subjects, and the Offices of both, to be had in equal reſpect, though the vertues of the one ſort, be to be preferred before the vices of the other.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Protection is not the ground of Subjection. That ſpeech, <hi>ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus populi, ſuprema lex,</hi> doth not detract from the Supremacy of Kings, nor juſtifie the contumacy of Subjects: but the genuine ſenſe thereof is this, that the ſafety of the people ſhould be the ſcope of Legiſlators; whoſe Laws ſhould conduce thereunto.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>A Simili:</hi> If a <hi>Maſter</hi> exerciſe too much <hi>rigour</hi> toward his <hi>Servants,</hi> ſhall they therefore <hi>caſt off</hi> the yoke of <hi>Subjection?</hi> The Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> exhortech otherwiſe. Be ſubject to your Maſters,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.18.</note> 
               <hi>not only</hi> to the <hi>good,</hi> and to the
<hi>gentle,</hi> but to the <hi>froward.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If a <hi>Father</hi> provoke his children to wrath, and give them im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moderate and undeſerved Correction, ſhall they therefore <hi>break the Bond of Filial Subjection, diſown</hi> his
<hi>Paternal Juriſdiction,</hi> and <hi>Abſalom-like</hi> riſe up in <hi>Rebellion</hi> againſt him? <hi>God forbid.</hi> In like manner, a <hi>Political Fathers violation of his truſt,</hi> is no ground for <hi>Subjects violation of their duty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. There is a <hi>general good</hi> attained by the Government of the <hi>worſt Princes,</hi> which doth <hi>over-ballance</hi> all their <hi>Perſonal Fail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Zedekiah,</hi> an evil King, is called by <hi>Jeremiah,</hi> the <hi>Breath of the Iſraelites Noſtrils.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lam.</hi> 4.20.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Without Government,</hi> men would be like <hi>wild beaſts</hi> in the wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs, and like <hi>Fiſhes</hi> in the Sea, the <hi>ſtronger</hi> devouring the <hi>wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker. Praeſtat ſub male Principe eſſe, quam ſub nullo,</hi> Corn. Tac. Lib. 1. Hiſt.</p>
            <p>Wherefore to endeavour the redreſs of Irregularities, and <hi>male-adminiſtrations</hi> of Government, by diſmounting or deſtroying the Governour, is a <hi>Remedy worſe then the Diſeaſe:</hi> it is to cure a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtemper in the Head by cutting it off.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The <hi>Providence of God</hi> is often <hi>judicially</hi> exerciſed in ſetting evil Kings over a Nation, as a puniſhment of the ſins thereof.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 3.4. Compared with <hi>Ec.</hi> 10.16. <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 13.11.</note> God threatneth wo to a Land, by giving Children to be their Princes, and Babes to rule over them,
<hi>i. e.</hi> Fooliſh and Froward Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I gave them a King in mine anger.</hi> Theſe words do not argue, Gods diſpleaſure againſt <hi>Monarchy;</hi> for he gave <hi>Iſrael, David</hi> and <hi>Solomon,</hi> and other Kings, <hi>not</hi> in <hi>Anger,</hi> but in <hi>Love</hi> and <hi>Mercy.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1
<hi>Kin.</hi> 10.9</note> Becauſe the Lord <hi>loved Iſrael,</hi> therefore made he thee
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:96629:20"/>
               <hi>King,</hi> ſaith the <hi>Queen</hi> of <hi>Sheba</hi> to
<hi>Solomon.</hi> But the ſcope of them, is to ſhew, that for the ſins of the
<hi>Iſraelites,</hi> the Lord ſet over them <hi>Saul,</hi> a <hi>fierce man,</hi> that handled them in ſuch a <hi>rigorous</hi> manner, as is expreſſed in 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 8.10. to 18.</p>
            <p>Perſons groaning under Oppreſſion, and revenging themſelves on their Rulers, and not looking to the Judicial Providence of God, are like <hi>Dogs</hi> that <hi>ſnarle</hi> at the
<hi>ſtone,</hi> but <hi>look not</hi> to the <hi>hand</hi> that threw it.</p>
            <p n="5">5. God hath <hi>reſerved Kings for his own Tribunal,</hi> and not expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed them to the
<hi>tumultuous rage</hi> of the Common people. Againſt <hi>thee,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſ.</hi> 51.4.</note> and <hi>thee only</hi> have I ſinned, and done evil, in
<hi>thy</hi> ſight. <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> had ſinned againſt <hi>Uriah,</hi> by depriving him of his <hi>wife</hi> and <hi>life;</hi> but becauſe he was <hi>above</hi> the
<hi>juriſdiction</hi> of his <hi>Subjects;</hi> and his offence came under the
<hi>Cognizance</hi> of <hi>God alone,</hi> therefore he ſaith, againſt thee only have I ſinned.</p>
            <p>The Lord ſhall ſmite him,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Sa.</hi> 24.12.</note> or his day ſhall come, mine hand ſhall not be upon him.</p>
            <p n="6">6. The unanimous Suffrage of <hi>Holy Patriarchs, Prophets Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, Primitive Chriſtians,</hi> and of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt himſelf,</hi> may be produced againſt Subjects Rebellion againſt their King, under pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of Tyranny.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Abraham prayeth for Abimelech</hi> King of <hi>Gerar. Jacob bleſseth Pharaoh</hi> King of
<hi>Aegypt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 20.17.</note> notwithſtanding they were both
<hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Jeremiah</hi> and <hi>Daniel</hi> aſſert the Authority of <hi>Nebuchadnezzar,</hi> an
<hi>Idolater,</hi> a Tyrant, and a deſtroyer and depopulator of Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries. Thou,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dan.</hi> 2.37.</note> O King, art a King of Kings; for the God of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven hath given thee a Kingdom. Thoſe Nations that will not ſerve,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jer.</hi> 27.6,
8, 9.</note> and put their necks under the yoke of the King of <hi>Babylon,</hi> ſhall be puniſhed with the Sword, and with Famine, and with Peſtilence, until they be conſumed. Therefore hearken not to your <hi>Diviners,</hi> nor to your <hi>Dreamers,</hi> nor to your
<hi>Enchanters,</hi> nor to your <hi>Sorcerers,</hi> which ſay unto you, <hi>ye ſhall not ſerve the King of Babylon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The holy Apoſtles <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi> command Subjection to <hi>hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then Emperors:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.1, 2, 3. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.13, 17.</note> For it was about 300 years after Chriſt, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently a long time after the death of the Apoſtles, before any Magiſtrates became Chriſtians.</p>
            <p>The Primitive Chriſtians were wont to pray for Pagan Princes, <hi>Exoptantes ipſis vitam prolixam, imperium ſecurum, domum tutam, exercitus fortes, Senatum fidelem, populum probum, &amp; orbem quie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum,</hi>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:96629:20"/>Tertul. Apologet. <hi>Cap.</hi> 30.</p>
            <p>Eminent was the example of <hi>Mephiboſheths</hi> Loyal deportment toward <hi>David,</hi> notwithſtanding he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> unjuſtly
<hi>ſequeſtred</hi> half his eſtate. The King ſaid,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Sam.</hi>
19.29, 30.</note> why ſpeakeſt thou any more of thy mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters? I have ſaid, thou and
<hi>Ziba</hi> divide the Land. And <hi>Mephi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boſheth</hi> ſaith, yea, let him take all, foraſmuch as my Lord the King is come again to his Houſe in peace.</p>
            <p>Our Saviour Jeſus Chriſt commandeth the payment of Tribute unto <hi>Caeſar.</hi> Give unto
<hi>Caeſar,</hi> the things that are <hi>Caeſars.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi>
22.21.</note> And acknowledgeth, that <hi>Pilate,</hi> an unjuſt <hi>Judge,</hi> had his
<hi>Commiſſion from Heaven.</hi> Thou couldeſt have no power againſt me,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>John</hi> 19.11.</note> unleſs it were given thee of God.</p>
            <p>The barbarous <hi>Jews</hi> themſelves, who crucified the Lord of Life, being asked by
<hi>Pilate,</hi> whether they would have their King to be crucified, anſwered, we have no King but <hi>Caeſar;</hi> intimating, that if they had believed, that Chriſt was their King, no violence ſhould have been offered unto him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rehoboam</hi> threatned Tyranny unto <hi>Iſrael,</hi> ſaying, my little finger ſhall be thicker than my Fathers Loyns; my Father chaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed you with whips, but I will chaſtiſe you with Scorpions; yet the <hi>Revolt</hi> of the ten Tribes from him, is called
<hi>Rebellion,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 13.4, 5, 7.</note> and the
<hi>Promoters</hi> thereof <hi>Sons of Belial. Ahab</hi> and <hi>Jezebel</hi> were as great
<hi>Oppreſſors,</hi> and as bloody <hi>Perſecutors</hi> of the Prophets, as ever held Scepter; yet God threatneth to puniſh <hi>Jehn</hi> for deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them and their Poſterity.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 1.4.</note> I will avenge the bloud of
<hi>Jezreel</hi> on the Houſe of <hi>Jehu,</hi> and will cauſe the Kingdom to ceaſe from the Houſe of <hi>Iſrael.</hi> Though the defection of the ten Tribes from the Houſe of
<hi>David,</hi> was the puniſhment of <hi>Solomons</hi> Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, and the deſtruction of
<hi>Ahab</hi> and <hi>Iezebel,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Kin.</hi> 11.11</note> the Judgment of God on them, for their Cruelty to <hi>Naboth:</hi> Yet this did no more excuſe the Treaſon of the ten Tribes and <hi>Jehu,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Kings</hi> 21.19, 21.</note> who out of rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons minds, executed theſe Judgments, than Gods <hi>predeterminati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> of the death of Chriſt, did juſtifie <hi>Judas</hi> betraying him, or the <hi>Jews</hi> crucifying him.</p>
            <p>So then we conclude, that in caſe of private and perſonal, or publick and National Injuries received from a King, Subjects ought to lay aſide all Malice, Guile, Envy, Evil Speakings,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.1.</note> and all weapons of War, and Inſtruments of death. Jeſus ſaith to one of his Diſciples, reſiſting the Officers of the Chief Prieſts and Elders of the <hi>Jews,</hi> that were ſent to apprehend him; Put up thy ſword into its place, for all they that take the ſword, ſhall periſh
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:96629:21"/>with the ſword.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.52.</note> 
               <hi>Preces &amp; Lachrima</hi> were the only Arms that the Primitive Chriſtians uſed, when they were oppreſſed and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted. <hi>Humiliation, Ref<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>ion</hi> and <hi>Supplication</hi> unto God, who judgeth among the gods, and in whoſe hands are the hearts of Kings,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prov.</hi> 21.1.</note> who turneth them as Rivers of water, are better Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dients for the removal of Preſſures from a Nation, than Rebellion. <hi>Samuel</hi> having in the precedent verſes foretold to the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> the rigorous carriage of their King towards them,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 8.18.</note> he ſaith, ye ſhall <hi>cry out</hi> in that day, becauſe of your King, but the Lord will not
<hi>hear</hi> you: he doth not ſay, ye ſhall <hi>riſe up</hi> and <hi>depoſe your King,</hi> but ye ſhall <hi>cry</hi> unto the Lord for Relief.</p>
            <p>A provoked Prince ought to be <hi>pacified</hi> by <hi>Submiſſion,</hi> not
<hi>irri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tated</hi> by <hi>Revenge,</hi> which is not lawful againſt a <hi>Private Perſon,</hi> much leſs againſt the <hi>Head of a Nation:</hi> For a Subject lying un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der groundleſs ſuſpitions, to infer from thence, that it is better to be ſuſpected for
<hi>ſomthing,</hi> than <hi>nothing,</hi> is the <hi>Devils Logick;</hi> and to exerciſe Rebellion <hi>correſpondent</hi> to ſuch a Principle, is a <hi>dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolical Fact.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Mens ſubmiſſive deportment, and ſedulous endeavours, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move even the cauſleſs Jealouſies of their Prince, is the moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable means to ſtir up the <hi>Embers of Ingenuity</hi> in his heart. A <hi>Flint</hi> will <hi>break</hi> upon a <hi>Featherbed.</hi> No heart can be ſo <hi>Ada<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mantine,</hi> as to withſtand the force of an Argument drawn from
<hi>do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing good for evil.</hi> This, like a <hi>Sun-beam</hi> melted the ſpirit of <hi>Saul</hi> himſelf. <hi>Saul</hi> ſaid, is this thy voice, my Son <hi>David?</hi> and he lift up his voice and wept:<note place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 24.16, 17, 18, 19.</note> And ſaid to <hi>David,</hi> thou art more righteous than I; for thou haſt rewarded me good, whereas I have rewarded thee evil; and thou haſt ſhewed this day, that thou haſt dealt well with me; foraſmuch as when the Lord delivered me into thy hands, thou killedſt me not: For if a man find his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, will he let him go free?<note place="margin">1 <hi>Sa.</hi> 26.21.</note> Again, I have ſinned, return my Son <hi>David,</hi> for I will no more do thee harm, becauſe my ſoul was precious in thine eyes: Behold, I have played the fool, and erred exceedingly. Herein the words of <hi>Solomon</hi> are verified. <hi>By long for bearing a Prince is beſt perſwaded.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prov.</hi> 25.15.</note> But a revengeful retalia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Injuries, will
<hi>exasperate</hi> the Spirits of <hi>Princes,</hi> who being <hi>Cedars in Lebanon,</hi> will diſdain to receive <hi>affronts</hi> from <hi>Thiſtles in Lebanon.</hi> Wherefore that Admonition in <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 10.4. is not only <hi>moſt pious</hi> and <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> but alſo <hi>moſt prudential. If the spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of a Ruler riſe up againſt thee, leave not thy place,</hi> (<hi>i. e.</hi> flee not away in rage and paſſion) <hi>for yielding pacifieth great offences.</hi> Now
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:96629:21"/>this Prerogative of Princes, to wit, their exemption from the violence of their Subjects, ſhould be a <hi>golden Bridle</hi> to <hi>reſtrain</hi> them from all actions
<hi>exorbitant</hi> and <hi>excentrical</hi> from Juſtice and equity, and a golden ſpur to quicken them to ſuch Heroical acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, for the publick good, that may argue them to be of
<hi>Noble and Prince-like spirits,</hi> as well as of <hi>Noble and Princely Blood</hi> and
<hi>Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But bleſſed be the Lord, who hath ſet over <hi>England,</hi> not a <hi>Scratching Bramble,</hi> but a <hi>Royal Olive,</hi> whoſe Fatneſs and Sweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs doth rejoyce and
<hi>exhilerate</hi> our hearts: A <hi>Prince,</hi> that is, (as it was ſaid of <hi>Titus</hi> the
<hi>Roman</hi> Emperor) <hi>Deliciae generis huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni, the delight of mankind,</hi> in whom
<hi>Clemency, Wiſdom,</hi> and all other Royal endowments and Princely vertues are
<hi>concentricated.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Upon this account, I had almoſt reſolved to omit the proſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of this Point, as uſeleſs to a People living under ſuch a <hi>Graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Soveraign:</hi> But conſidering, that the <hi>beſt managed Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> have been from the <hi>beginning,</hi> and will be to the
<hi>end</hi> of the world, <hi>obnoxious</hi> to ſome <hi>Imperfections,</hi> that there will be alwaies ſome <hi>detracting Abſaloms,</hi> who will <hi>calumniate</hi> and exclaim againſt the moſt righteous Rulers, that the prohibition of Rebellion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Tyrannical Governours doth <hi>a fortiori</hi> conclude for <hi>Englands</hi> Subjection to our preſent Gracious Soveraign, and laſtly, that this <hi>Crown-Jewel</hi> hath been much blemiſhed and
<hi>ſullied</hi> of late, I was, for theſe Reaſons, unwilling to leave it altogether
<hi>unpoliſhed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Conſider <hi>David</hi> as <hi>Anointed.</hi> Then <hi>Samuel</hi> took an horn of Oyl, and anointed him in the midſt of his Brethren. 1.<note place="margin">1 <hi>Sa.</hi>
16.13.</note> To a <hi>Prophetical.</hi> 2. To a <hi>Kingly Office.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. To a <hi>Prophetical Office.</hi> That Clauſe, the Spirit of the Lord came upon him from that day forward, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 16.13. denoteth the <hi>Gift of Propheſie,</hi> as appeareth, by comparing it with 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 19.20, 23. Where the like Expreſſion is uſed, to ſet forth the Gift of Propheſie in <hi>Saul</hi> and his Meſſengers, when they ſought
<hi>David</hi> at <hi>Naioth</hi> in <hi>Ramah. Davids Pſalmes</hi> were endited by a Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical Spirit: And he is expreſly called a Prophet. It was uſual,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 2.30.</note> for Prophets as well as Prieſts to be conſecrated unto their Office by Anointing. The Lord ſaith unto <hi>Elias,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Kings</hi>
19.16.</note> 
               <hi>Eliſha</hi> the Son of <hi>Shaphat,</hi> ſhalt thou anoint to be Prophet in thy room. Now foraſmuch as <hi>David</hi> a Prophet ſaith, God forbid that I ſhould ſtretch forth my hand againſt my Maſter; Obſerve,
<list>
                  <item>1. <hi>That Eccleſiaſtical perſons are not priviledged nor exempted from Subjection to the Civil Magiſtrate.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:96629:22"/>
                  <item>2. <hi>That ſuch, of all men, ſhould be chiefly ſolicitous to maintain Loyalty in themſelves, and to propagate it in others.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>That Eccleſiaſtical Perſons are not priviledged nor exempted from Subjection to the Civil Magistrate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let <hi>every</hi> ſoul be ſubject to the higher Power.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi>
13.1.</note> Every ſoul is <hi>em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phatically</hi> put for every man, as <hi>Exod.</hi> 1.5. All the ſouls that came out of <hi>Jacobs</hi> Loyns, were ſeventy ſouls, <hi>i. e.</hi> ſeventy per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons. Is not the Command <hi>general?</hi> Let every ſoul, whether <hi>rich</hi> or <hi>poor, Noble</hi> or <hi>Ignoble, Patritian</hi> or <hi>Plebeian, Political</hi> or
<hi>Eccleſiaſtical,</hi> be ſubject to the higher Powers. <hi>Non diſtinguendum eſt, ubi Scriptura non diſtinguit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We ſind no place of Scripture that doth except the <hi>Pope</hi> and his <hi>Cardinals</hi> out of this general Precept, except they diſclaim humane nature, and avouch themſelves to be
<hi>Angels, Cherubims</hi> or <hi>Sera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phims,</hi> as a Popiſh <hi>Poſtiller,</hi> out of
<hi>Exod.</hi> 30.31. hath done, where it is ſaid of the holy Oyl; Upon mans fleſh it ſhall not be poured, thou ſhalt anoint <hi>Aaron</hi> and his Sons; from hence he ridiculouſly inferreth, that Prieſts are Angels, not having humane fleſh.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Aaron</hi> the <hi>High Prieſt</hi> acknowledged the Juriſdiction of <hi>Moſes</hi> over him, when he was reproved for making the Golden Calf. <hi>Aaron</hi> ſaid,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ex.</hi> 32.22.</note> Let not the Anger of <hi>my Lord</hi> wax hot.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>King Solomon depoſed Abiathar from the Priesthood,</hi> for conſpiring with
<hi>Adonijah.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Kings</hi> 2.26, 35.</note>
            </p>
            <p>What <hi>Antipodes</hi> do the Popes tread hereunto, in preſuming to depoſe Kings. The Kings of <hi>Judah</hi> exerciſed their Authority <hi>in ſpiritualibus,</hi> as well as <hi>in temporalibus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Aſa, Hezekiah, Jehoſaphat, Joſiah,</hi> reformed Religion, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed the high places,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 17. 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 18. 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 13.1, 2, 3.
2 <hi>Chr.</hi> 29.4. 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 29.</note> and Monuments of Idolatry, and convo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated Synods. So Chriſtian Emperors, <hi>Conſtantine, Theodoſius,</hi> and others have convented General Councils. <hi>Hezekiah</hi> laid in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junctions on the Prieſts and Levites to perform their duties.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Paul</hi> being arraigned before <hi>Feſtus, Felix</hi> and <hi>Agrippa,</hi> plead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not an exemption from the Juriſdiction of their Courts, by vertue of his <hi>Apoſtolical Office.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>His free and voluntary Appeal to <hi>Ceſar,</hi> argueth, his acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgment of ſubjection to earthly Rulers. Jeſus Chriſt paied tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute for himſelf and <hi>Peter,</hi> that he might not incourage the <hi>Jews</hi> to deny it, nor the <hi>Romans</hi> to defie the Goſpel, as deſtructive to Magiſtracy.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 17.27.</note> That Expreſſion,
<hi>then are the Children free,</hi> doth ſhew the <hi>Prerogative</hi> of Chriſt, as he was the Eternal Son of God,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:96629:22"/>but not the exemption of Gods adopted Children from <hi>ſecular Powers:</hi> For then Lay-men alſo (many of them being the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of God) muſt be exempted as well as the Clergy.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Reſervation</hi> of the Lands of the <hi>Aegyptian</hi> Prieſts from ſale, doth ſhew, the <hi>Munificence</hi> of their King, in that he aſſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to them a portion at his own Table; but their <hi>ſuperiority above,</hi> or <hi>coordination unto</hi> Civil Magiſtrates, cannot in any wiſe be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded from thence.</p>
            <p>Though ſome <hi>munificent Princes,</hi> out of their <hi>Indulgenoe,</hi> have granted large immunities unto the Church, yet let us do, as Chriſt in the caſe of Divorce, <hi>reduce</hi> Magiſtracy to its <hi>Original</hi> and <hi>Primitive Inſtitution,</hi> and we ſhall find, that from the beginning it had Juriſdiction over the Clergy as well as the Laity.</p>
            <p>How is the <hi>Arrogance</hi> of the <hi>Pope of Rome,</hi> that man of ſin, and Son of perdition, to be condemned, for that he exalteth himſelf <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, above all that is called god, or <hi>Auguſt, i. e.</hi> above Kings and Emperots. The Papiſts hold,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 24.</note> that the Eccleſiaſtical State is as much more excellent, than the Civil, as the <hi>Sun</hi> than the <hi>Moon;</hi> and that as the Moon borroweth its Light from the Sun, ſo the Emperors receive their power from the Pope, who employeth the <hi>Jeſuites his ſlaughter-ſlaves,</hi> to mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der thoſe Princes, that deny his Supremacy, or affront his Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; Witneſs the Murder of <hi>Henry</hi> the 4th. King of
<hi>France,</hi> by <hi>Ravilliack,</hi> and the <hi>Gunpowder-plot</hi> contrived by
<hi>Garnet</hi> the Jeſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ite, and others, his Complices, for the deſtruction of <hi>King James.</hi> The Popes Affronts unto, Excommunications of, Incroachments on, and imperious Domination over Princes, are ſo notorious, that I need not recite Examples thereof. <hi>Sed exorto Evangelii jubare ſagaciores, ut ſpero, Princepes ad nutum Romani Orbilii non ſolvent ſubligaoula.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hiſtory affords manifold Inſtances of the Arrogance of Popes, how they have
<hi>trampled</hi> on the Necks of Kings, <hi>kicked</hi> off their Crowns, and crowned them with their Feet, forced them to hold their <hi>Stirrups,</hi> and to dance attendance at their gates,
<hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicated, depoſed</hi> them,<note place="margin">Mat. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> and <hi>(in imitation of the Devil)</hi> diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed of their Kingdoms, <hi>abſolved</hi> their Subjects from obedience, and <hi>chained</hi> their <hi>Ambaſſadors,</hi> like <hi>Dogs</hi> under their Tables. How do they herein <hi>deviate</hi> from the Example of Saint <hi>Peter,</hi> whoſe Succeſſors they pretend to be: and of the holy Prophet <hi>David,</hi> who calleth King
<hi>Saul</hi> his <hi>Maſter?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>That Ministers of all men,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Obſerv. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>ſhould chiefly be ſolicitous to maintain
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:96629:23"/>Loyalty in themſelves, and to propagate it in others.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>David</hi> a Prophet, preacheth a Sermon of Loyalty to his Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers. Miniſters have great opportunity to <hi>expelſeditious,</hi> and <hi>inſtil loyal</hi> Principles into the hearts of their Auditors. The <hi>Reverence</hi> that people bear unto their <hi>holy Function,</hi> will <hi>facilitate</hi> the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainment of their Inſtructions.</p>
            <p>The <hi>benevolence</hi> of Chriſtian <hi>Princes</hi> to the Church, in protect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Miniſtry from the fury of groſſely prophane, and giddy Fanatick people (to whom it is an
<hi>eye-ſore</hi>) in ſupplying the Church with maintenance, in order to the carrying on the Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God, in providing <hi>Univerſities</hi> and <hi>Colledges,</hi> to be
<hi>Semi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naries</hi> of Learning, in backing the Laws of God with their ſecular Authority, doth lay ſtrong Obligations on Miniſters, to make their <hi>Churches Schools,</hi> as of <hi>Piety toward God,</hi> ſo of <hi>Loyalty toward their King.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What horrid ingratitude would Miniſters be guilty of, by pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving <hi>fire-brands</hi> of Sedition, <hi>Trumpeters</hi> of Rebellion, and by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king their <hi>Sermons</hi> an <hi>Alarm</hi> unto war? It would be, to <hi>rip up the bowels</hi> of their Nurſing Fathers, and to <hi>cut off the Breasts</hi> of their Nurſing Mothers.</p>
            <p>Furthermore, as <hi>Simeon and Levi</hi> made the Name of their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Jacob</hi> to ſtink,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 34.30. <hi>Num.</hi> 13.32</note> by their perfidious Murder of the <hi>Shechemites,</hi> as the Spies brought an evil report on the Land of
<hi>Canaan,</hi> and as <hi>Judas</hi> delivered his Maſter unto the Scoffes of his enemies, ſo diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loyalty in Eccleſiaſtical perſons, ſcandalizeth Religion. The ſins of
<hi>Elies</hi> Sons cauſed the Sacrifices of the Lord to be abhorred.<note place="margin">1
<hi>Sam.</hi> 2.17.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The Prophet <hi>Davids</hi> Adultery with <hi>Bathſheba,</hi> and Murder of
<hi>Uriah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.17. to 25.</note> gave great occaſion to the enemies of God to blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheme.</p>
            <p>For Miniſters to <hi>prostitute</hi> their Sacred Function unto Ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Rebellion, is a great provocation unto Magiſtrates, to root them out of their Kingdoms, yea, to put them to death, as <hi>Saul</hi> did <hi>Ahimelech,</hi> and the Prieſts of the Lord, of whom he ſlew fourſcore and five perſons, upon <hi>Doegs</hi> falſe and malicious infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, that they conſpired with <hi>David.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Sa.</hi> 22.18.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Let <hi>Sermons</hi> be <hi>Exclamations</hi> againſt <hi>ſins,</hi> not againſt
<hi>Kings,</hi> againſt the <hi>Prince of the power of the Air,</hi> not againſt the
<hi>Princes of the earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Lord teach the Clergy of <hi>England,</hi> not only <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, but alſo
<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that they may neither procure the accuſation of diſloyalty to themſelves, nor derive any ſcandal unto Religion.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:96629:23"/> Let no man be lifted up with pride, by reaſon of the dignity of his Office.
<hi>Judas caſt Devils out of others,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 22.3.</note> 
               <hi>but could not keep the Devil out of himſelf.</hi> Then Satan entred into <hi>Judas,</hi> and ſo (as
<hi>Luther</hi> ſaith) <hi>there was one Devil in another.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As water cleanſeth other things, and then is crſt into the ſink, as many who laboured in building <hi>Noahs</hi> Ark, were drowned in the Floud, ſo a Miniſter may teach others, and yet be himſelf a caſt-away, without true Piety, which is inconſiſtent with diſloy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty. The Scripture hath linked them both together: My Son, <hi>fear</hi> thou <hi>God</hi> and the
<hi>King.</hi> It was the honour of <hi>Zadok</hi> and <hi>Abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>athar,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prov.
<hi>24.</hi>
               </note> that they turned not aſide unto <hi>Abſalom,</hi> but faithfully cleaved unto <hi>David,</hi> their rightful Soveraign.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>David</hi> was anointed to the Office of a King. The Lord ſaid unto
<hi>Samuel,</hi> how long wilt thou mourn for <hi>Saul,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi>
16.1.</note> ſeeing I have rejected him from reigning over <hi>Iſrael.</hi> Fill thine Horn with Oyl, and go, I will ſend thee to <hi>Jeſſe</hi> the <hi>Bethlehemite;</hi> for I have provided me a King among his Sons.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>David</hi> by vertue of this Unction had a plauſible Argument, to have juſtified the Murder of <hi>Saul,</hi> being <hi>rejected</hi> by God, and himſelf
<hi>elected</hi> in his room, and to have repreſented ſuch an act, as the execution of Juſtice, as <hi>Jehu</hi> did the deſtruction of <hi>Ahabt</hi> poſterity. But <hi>David</hi> abhorred this obvious plece of Policy,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Kin.</hi> 10.10</note> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it would have been a breach of Piety: Foraſmuch as <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations</hi> are no
<hi>Commiſſions.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 4.15.</note> Whoſoever ſhall ſlay (accurſed) <hi>Cain,</hi> vengeince ſhall be taken on him ſeven fold: So the bloud of rejected <hi>Saul</hi> would have brought down vengeance on the head of <hi>David,</hi> if he had ſhed it.</p>
            <p>The crucifying of Chriſt was an Act of <hi>Glorious Mercy</hi> in God, but of <hi>barbarous Cruelty</hi> in the <hi>Jews.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Joſeph</hi> tels his Brethren, that it was not they, but God, that ſent him into
<hi>Egypt,</hi> and yet they were guilty of the moſt unbro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly act, next to actual Fratricide, that ever was committed.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 45.8.</note> One, and the ſame action may be <hi>righteous,</hi> as it proceedeth from the <hi>firſt cauſe,</hi> and
<hi>unrighteous</hi> in reſpect of the <hi>Second.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Gods bidding <hi>Shimei</hi> to curſe <hi>David,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 12.11,
12.</note> and permiſſion of <hi>Abſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lom</hi> to raviſh his Fathers Concubines, were
<hi>acts of Juſtice</hi> in God, but <hi>acts of Treaſon</hi> and <hi>Inceſt</hi> in
<hi>Shimel</hi> and <hi>Abſalom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherefore let ſuch be accounted <hi>Inſtruments of the Devil,</hi>
               <note place="margin">&amp;

<hi>Ch.</hi> 16.10.</note> who dare offer violence to Kings, under <hi>pretence</hi> of being
<hi>Inſtruments</hi> to <hi>execute</hi> divine <hi>Juſtice.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>David</hi> by vertue of his Unction, might have produced a
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:96629:24"/>ſpecious Title unto the Kingdom of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> if he had been of an ambitious ſpirit; but he knew that he was anointed only to the <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion</hi> of the Kingdom; and that as a <hi>laſt Will and Teſtament</hi> is of <hi>no force,</hi> until the
<hi>death</hi> of the <hi>Teſtator:</hi> So his Unction was of no force until the death of
<hi>Saul.</hi> A Loyal Subject will <hi>wave obvious Pleas</hi> for his Right unto a Kingdom.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>David</hi> being anointed to the reverſion of the Kingdom by the death of
<hi>Saul,</hi> might have took <hi>Livery</hi> and <hi>Seiſin</hi> of it: But as <hi>Moſes</hi> caſt the Kingdom of <hi>Egypt,</hi> with all the Honours and Treaſures thereof, at his heels; chuſing rather to ſuffer affliction with the people of God, than to enjoy the pleaſures of ſin for a ſeaſon;<note place="margin">Heb. <hi>11.</hi>
               </note> So <hi>David</hi> preſerred the <hi>prolongation</hi> of his undeſerved <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution,</hi> before the <hi>unjuſt acceleration</hi> of the day of his <hi>Inauguration</hi> unto the Office of a King; he eſteemed a <hi>Turfe</hi> in the <hi>wilderneſs,</hi> with a <hi>clear Conſcience,</hi> a better ſeat, than a <hi>Throne</hi> in a <hi>Palace,</hi> with a <hi>Conſcience laden</hi> with <hi>Royal Blood-guiltineſs;</hi> he accounted it a greater honour, to be a <hi>Loyal Subject,</hi> than an
<hi>unlawful King.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Crowns, Scepters and Kingdoms, are cogent Temptations. <hi>Caeſar</hi> ſaid, If Juſtice may be broken in any caſe, it is <hi>regnandi cauſa.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi>
21.38.</note> The Husbandmen cry out, This is the <hi>Heir,</hi> come let us kill him, and the
<hi>Inheritance</hi> will be <hi>ours.</hi> But <hi>David</hi> abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to <hi>ſwim</hi> unto a
<hi>Throne through the Blood</hi> of his <hi>Master,</hi> having taken the reſolution of
<hi>Ferdinand the firſt, Emperor of Germany: Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at Juſtitia, &amp; pereat mundus.</hi> Let Right be done, and come what will of it.</p>
            <p>The gain of a Kingdom will not <hi>countervail</hi> the loſs of a good Conſcience. What will it profit a man to gain the whole world, and loſe his own Soul? Or what will be given in exchange for the Soul? There is a <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in the words; What will it profit? <hi>i. e.</hi> What an hard bargain will it be? What infinite Damage and Detriment ſhall a man ſuſtain thereby? For put the whole world into one ballance, and the Soul into another, and this little
<hi>ſpark</hi> of <hi>Divinity</hi> will out-weigh the whole <hi>Globe</hi> of the Earth, the vaſt Fabrick of the Creation.</p>
            <p>It is far better to be upbraided, as <hi>Balaam</hi> was by <hi>Balak,</hi> The <hi>Lord</hi> hath <hi>kept</hi> thee <hi>back</hi> from <hi>Honour,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Num.</hi>
24.11</note> than to be told at the day of Judgment, That <hi>Honour</hi> hath <hi>kept</hi> us
<hi>back</hi> from the <hi>Lord,</hi> from <hi>Heaven</hi> and <hi>everlaſting Happineſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Crown is not worth the taking up, on <hi>ſordid,</hi> much leſs, on <hi>ſinful</hi> terms. It is enough for a bloudy <hi>Phocas</hi> to ſlay his Maſter
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:96629:24"/>
               <hi>Mauritius,</hi> that he might obtain the Succeſſion in the Empire: For
<hi>Pagan Emperors</hi> and <hi>Antichriſtian Popes</hi> to <hi>poyſon</hi> one another (as
<hi>Hildebrand</hi> poyſoned 7 <hi>Popes,</hi> to get into the Papal Chair) for their own advancement. Godly <hi>David</hi> valued his Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and the glory of God at a greater price, than to wound them, for any temporal Emolument: Even as <hi>Jonathan</hi> did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him; who being Heir apparent to the Kingdom of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and knowing that <hi>David</hi> was appointed to ſet him beſides the Throne, as appeareth by his Fathers Information:<note place="margin">1 <hi>Sa.</hi> 20.30, 31.</note> Thou haſt choſen the Son of <hi>Jeſſe</hi> to thy own Confuſion; for as long as he liveth, thou ſhalt not be eſtabliſhed, nor thy Kingdom: And by his own Confeſſion, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 23.17. Yet would not conſpire with
<hi>Saul</hi> againſt <hi>Davids</hi> Life; but contracteth cloſe friendſhip with him, loveth him as his own Soul, giveth him intelligence of his Fathers deſignes, pleadeth his cauſe, vindicateth his Innocen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, proclaimeth his Merits, and ſaveth his life,<note place="margin">1
<hi>Sa.</hi> 20.33.</note> by the hazard of his own, and by the loſs of his Kingdom. <hi>O bravely acted Noble Jonathan!</hi> How doth thy <hi>Heroical Self-denial</hi> condemn all thoſe, who lay wait for bloud, and lurk privily for the Innocent without a cauſe, and ſwallow them up alive as the grave, and whole as thoſe that go down into the pir, that they may find all precious ſubſtance, and fill their Houſes with Treaſure? Eſpecially,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pr.</hi> 1.11, 12, 13.</note> thoſe bloudy and ambitious men, who cut off the head of their Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign, for the ſake of his Royal Crown upon it, even as a man breaketh a Branch from a Tree, for the ſake of the Fruit, which groweth thereon.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Oh</hi> the curſed <hi>Idolatry</hi> of <hi>Jeroboam,</hi> who to eſtabliſh his own
<hi>Throne,</hi> ſet up <hi>another</hi> for the <hi>Devil,</hi> by erecting Calves at
<hi>Dan</hi> and <hi>Bethel!</hi> Oh the barbarous cruelty of <hi>Herod,</hi> and of
<hi>Pharaoh,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 2. <hi>Exod.</hi> 1.</note> who for their own Security, <hi>maſſacred</hi> ſo many innocent <hi>Infants,</hi> that knew not their right hand from their left! Oh <hi>England!</hi> How barren haſt thou been of <hi>Self-denying Jonathans</hi> and <hi>Davids,</hi> theſe late years! And how haſt thou exceeded
<hi>Affrica,</hi> in the ingendring of <hi>Monſters! Monſters,</hi> like unto <hi>Ahab</hi> and
<hi>Jezebel,</hi> who for an <hi>Acre</hi> or <hi>two</hi> of ground, ſhed the <hi>Blood</hi> of
<hi>Naboth.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Kings</hi> 21.</note> And like unto <hi>Judas,</hi> who for Thirty Pieces of Silver, ſold our <hi>Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours Body,</hi> and <hi>his own Soul.</hi> Yea, ſuch Monſters, whoſe Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons would almoſt make us believe, that they had compacted with the Devil, for the Kingdoms of the world, upon thoſe terms, which he propoſed to Jeſus Chriſt. And whoſe Rage,<note place="margin">Mat. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> Ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Cruelty did ſpeak aloud, that to gain a Kingdom, they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:96629:25"/>not, though the <hi>Streets</hi> did <hi>run</hi> with <hi>Bloud,</hi> in ſtead of the <hi>Conduits</hi> with <hi>Wine</hi> at the Coronation.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The Fourth General Head obſerved in the Analyſis of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vids</hi> Oration, containeth the Reaſons of his deteſtation of cutting off the Royal Head of King <hi>Saul;</hi> which are drawn from <hi>Sauls</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>To himſelf: My Maſter.</hi> This word denotes that chief power which men have over their Servants.</p>
            <p>Obſerve,<note place="margin">Obſerv.</note> 
               <hi>That Kings are inveſted with Supreme Power and Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign Authority over their Subjects.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>They are called gods, to ſhew their preheminence over their Subjects, who ought to account of them as <hi>pleni-potentiary</hi> Ambaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſadots of the Supream Jehovah.<note place="margin">1
<hi>Pet.</hi> 2.13.</note> Submit your ſelves to every Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance of man for the Lords ſake, whether unto the <hi>King,</hi> as <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prems.</hi> Where the word of a King is,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 8.4.</note> there is <hi>power:</hi> and who may ſay unto him, what doſt thou? This power of Kings is both Legiſlative and Executive.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Legiſlative</hi> or Nomothetical, The Laws of Kings oblige the Conſciences of Subjects.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.5.</note> Ye muſt be ſubject, not only for
<hi>wrath,</hi> but for <hi>Conſcience-ſake.</hi> And be ye ſubject to every Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of man for the <hi>Lords ſake.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.13.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Executive.</hi> As <hi>Swords</hi> are worn both for <hi>Ornament</hi> and
<hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence:</hi> So the <hi>execution of Laws</hi> is both the <hi>priviledge</hi> and the
<hi>du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> of Princes. Good Laws not duly executed, are to no more purpoſe than a <hi>ruſty Sword,</hi> that cannot be drawn out of the Scab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bard.</p>
            <p>Now this Legiſlative and executive Authority of Kings extend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not only to <hi>Civil Matters,</hi> as the <hi>deciſion</hi> of Controverſies ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing between man and man, and
<hi>criminal,</hi> as the puniſhment of Malefactors, even with Capital puniſhment; but alſo to <hi>Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtical Affairs.</hi> Thus the Regal Authority of <hi>David, Aſa, Jeho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaphat; Hezekiah</hi> and <hi>Joſiah</hi> was <hi>exerted</hi> in the <hi>extirpation</hi> of Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry, <hi>eſtabliſhment</hi> of the true Worſhip of God, <hi>compulſion</hi> of the Prieſts and People to diſcharge their mutual duties; and in the <hi>Convocation of Synods,</hi> with other Acts of <hi>Juriſdiction.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A King without Supreme Power, is but <hi>magni nominis umbra,</hi> and his Office, but a
<hi>Titular</hi> dignity, but the <hi>Feathers</hi> of Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity.</p>
            <p>The Uſurpation of a Tyrant, who aſſumeth unto himſelf <hi>power, without a Title,</hi> is fatal to a <hi>Kingdom.</hi> And the Government of a King, who hath a <hi>Title without power,</hi> to defend it, is fatal to <hi>himſelf.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:96629:25"/> As <hi>Might without Right, is Tyranny,</hi> ſo <hi>Right without Might, is Pageantry,</hi> but the Picture of a King.</p>
            <p>A King <hi>manacled</hi> and <hi>fettered</hi> (if I may ſo ſpeak) cannot pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tect himſelf, much leſs his Subjects.</p>
            <p>His <hi>Perſon</hi> will be expoſed to violence, his <hi>Government</hi> to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt, and the Execution of Laws, the <hi>Nerves</hi> and <hi>Ligaments</hi> of a <hi>Realm</hi> obſtructed: His Throne would be <hi>invaded</hi> by every <hi>inſolent Rebel,</hi> and himſelf
<hi>depoſed</hi> by every <hi>Popular Traytor:</hi> For as a <hi>Scabbard</hi> without a
<hi>Sword,</hi> and a <hi>Gun</hi> charged with Powder, without a <hi>Bullet,</hi> which may give a great Report, but will do no Execution: Such is <hi>Royal dignity,</hi> without <hi>Soveraign Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Shall a <hi>Paterfamilias</hi> claim a <hi>deſpotical</hi> power over his Family? and ſhall the great <hi>Pater patriae</hi> have his Regal Power <hi>clipt</hi> and <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridged?</hi> God forbid. With whom can Power be more ſafely intruſted, than with a juſt and prudent Prince? Surely not with the Common People, where it will prove as dangerous, as a <hi>knife</hi> in a
<hi>Childs,</hi> and a <hi>Sword</hi> in a <hi>mad mans</hi> hand, which will be uſed only to do miſchief.</p>
            <p>Our late Diſtractions have ſufficiently taught us, that <hi>Democra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical</hi> Government is a <hi>Soleciſme</hi> in <hi>Polity:</hi> and that <hi>Democracy</hi> and <hi>Anarchy</hi> are equipollent terms. Wherefore we conclude, that a King ought to be acknowledged Supreme in all his Dominions, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Apoſtle, &amp; our oaths of Allegiance, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And all that have taken the <hi>Oaths of Supremacy</hi> and <hi>Allegiance,</hi> muſt
<hi>ſubſcribe</hi> to this Doctrine, or elſe <hi>contract</hi> the guilt of Perjury.</p>
            <p>The Texts of Scripture alledged againſt this Truth, are groſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly perverted; we may ſay with <hi>Solomon,</hi> that as <hi>the wringing of the Noſe bringeth forth blood,</hi> ſo the wreſting of Scripture bringeth forth bloudy Tenents. The Lord ſaith unto
<hi>Jeremiah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jer.</hi> 1.10.</note> I have ſet thee over Nations and Kingdoms, to root out, and to pluck down, and to deſtroy. Theſe words are to be underſtood of the denun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciation of Gods Judgments by the mouth of <hi>Jeremiah,</hi> againſt wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Nations. Kings ſhall bow down to thee with their Faces to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the earth, and lick up the duſt of thy Feet:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 49.23.</note> Theſe Meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phorical Expreſſions do not ſignifie the <hi>ſubordination</hi> of Civil Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er unto Eccleſiaſtical; but only that Princes ſhall ſubmit unto the Laws of God, and account it their honour to be <hi>Patrons</hi> of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and Nurſing Fathers and Nurſing Mothers unto the Church.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The two-edged ſword in the hands of the Saints,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi>
139.9.</note> 
               <hi>to bind Kings in
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:96629:26"/>Chains, and Nobles in Fetters of Iron,</hi> is to be underſtood, not of a
<hi>Weapon of War,</hi> or Inſtrument of violence, but of the <hi>ſword of the Spirit,</hi> which is, <hi>the Word of God;</hi> which is ſaid to be quick and powerful,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.12.</note> ſharper than any two-edged ſword: It is a
<hi>Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual,</hi> not a <hi>Martial,</hi> a <hi>Theological,</hi> not a <hi>Polemical</hi> ſword, that is given to the Church, to bind Kings in Chains, and Nobles in Fetters of Iron, What, by corporal Impriſonment? God for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid, but by awakening their Conſciences, and convincing them, of the evil, guilt and danger of ſin; which in Scripture is ſet forth by ſpiritual Captivity.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 61.1.</note> The Spirit of the Lord is upon me, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he hath anointed me, to proclaim <hi>Liberty</hi> to the <hi>Captives,</hi> and the opening of the Priſon doors to them that are <hi>bound,</hi> that is, to <hi>file aſunder</hi> the Fetters, and to <hi>knock off</hi> the Chains of the guilt of ſins from the Conſcience; by the <hi>promulgation</hi> of <hi>Gospel-Grace,</hi> and pardoning Mercy.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Second Reaſon of <hi>Davids</hi> deteſtation againſt ſtretching forth his hand againſt <hi>Saul,</hi> is taken from <hi>Sauls Relation to God, the Lords Anointed:</hi> Which is <hi>ingeminated</hi> in the Text. <hi>Ingeminations</hi> do <hi>augment</hi> the force and ſignification of expreſſions: <hi>In bleſſing I will bleſs thee,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 22.17.</note> and <hi>in multiplying I will multiply thee,</hi> that is, I will <hi>certainly</hi> and <hi>greatly</hi> bleſs and multiply thee. As <hi>David</hi> by the fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent <hi>Iteration</hi> of <hi>Abſaloms</hi> name,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Sa.</hi>
18.33.</note> O my Son <hi>Abſalom,</hi> my Son, my Son <hi>Abſalom;</hi> would God I had died for thee, O <hi>Abſalom,</hi> my Son, my Son, did ſignifie his great ſorrow for his death: So by his <hi>duplication</hi> of theſe words, <hi>the Lords Anointed,</hi> he doth ſhew the great and awful reverence due to <hi>Saul,</hi> by reaſon of his Relation unto God. This expreſſion, the <hi>Lords Anointed,</hi> may be conſidered in a threefold reſpect:
<list>
                  <item>1. As it is a Title of Honour.</item>
                  <item>2. As it ſignifieth Gods Qualification of <hi>Saul</hi> for this Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice.</item>
                  <item>3. As it imports the Divine Original and Inſtitution of his Office.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. As it is a Title of Honour. It is an Epithere which is gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to Jeſus Chriſt himſelf.<note place="margin">Pſalm <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Chriſt</hi> is a word, that ſignifieth <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointed. David</hi> doth not <hi>exclaim</hi> againſt <hi>Saul,</hi> as a
<hi>Tyrant,</hi> a <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutor,</hi> as a <hi>devouring Lion,</hi> and a <hi>deſtroying Bear</hi> (though he received as much Injury from him, as ever any Subject did from a Prince) but maketh mention of him in a very <hi>reverent</hi> and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable manner.</p>
            <p>He was ſo far from wounding <hi>Sanls heart</hi> with the <hi>Sword of vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence,</hi>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:96629:26"/>that he would not wound his <hi>good Name</hi> with the <hi>Sword</hi> of his
<hi>Tongue:</hi> From whence note;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That the Language of Subjects, of, and to their Soveraign,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Obſerv.</note> 
               <hi>ought not to ſavour of Contempt and Inſolency, but of honour and reverence toward his Perſon and Office.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thou ſhalt not <hi>revile</hi> the <hi>gods,</hi> nor <hi>curſe</hi> the <hi>Ruler</hi> of thy peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ex.</hi> 22.28.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Auguſt</hi> Names of Kings ought not to be <hi>beſooted</hi> with the opprobrions and ignominious Titles of Traytors, Tyrants and U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurpers. <hi>Is it ſit to ſay to a King, thou art wicked, or to Princes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Job</hi> 34.18.</note> 
               <hi>ye are ungodly?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Take heed of <hi>painting</hi> ſuch in the <hi>ſhape</hi> of the <hi>Devil,</hi> who
<hi>wear</hi> the <hi>Livery</hi> of <hi>God:</hi> I have ſaid ye are gods.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſalm</hi> 82. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 49. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 34.23. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 78.71,
72. <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. <hi>Pſ.</hi> 82.6. <hi>Jude v.</hi> 8. 2 <hi>Sa.</hi> 21.17. <hi>Lam.</hi>
4.20.</note>
            </p>
            <p>With what honourable Titles hath the Holy Ghoſt adorned Rulers? They are called
<hi>Fathers,</hi> yea, and <hi>Nurſing Fathers,</hi> and <hi>Nurſing Mothers</hi> to a Nation;
<hi>Paſtors and Shepherds.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Sons of the moſt High, Dignities, the Light of Iſrael,</hi> or the <hi>Lamp</hi> or <hi>Candle</hi> of <hi>Iſrael.</hi> As the Sun is to the world, ſo is a King to his Kingdom, even the Fountain of Light and Life? <hi>The Breath of our Noſtrils.</hi> And here in my Text, the Lords Anointed.</p>
            <p>The Lord hath purpoſely <hi>dignified.</hi> Princes with theſe Names, <hi>betokening Majeſty</hi> and <hi>Preheminence,</hi> as with ſo many <hi>orient Pearls</hi> and
<hi>ſhining Diamonds</hi> and Jewels, to beget a reverence in us to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward them, and to
<hi>guard</hi> them from the <hi>virulent</hi> and inſolent Tongues of <hi>curſing Shimei</hi>'s. Wherefore, take heed that ye <hi>ſlander</hi> not the <hi>Footſteps</hi> of the Lords Anointed, nor reproach the Father of your Nation: For the eye that mocketh his Father, and deſpiſeth to obey his Mother, the Ravens of the Valleys ſhall pick it out, and the young Eagles ſhall eat it. Beware of revi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling thoſe ſacred perſons, on whom God hath accumulated ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Titles of Honour.</p>
            <p>Yea the Lord foreſeeing how many <hi>Malicious Doegs</hi> and <hi>bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſphemous Rabſhekahs,</hi> Kings would meet withal,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 21.6. <hi>Ex.</hi>
22.28. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 82.1. <hi>Pſ.</hi> 138.1. 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.4.</note> hath
<hi>baptized</hi> them with his <hi>own moſt Reverent</hi> and <hi>Glorious Name.</hi> The Lord ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in the Congregation of the Mighty, he judgeth among the <hi>gods.</hi> Before the
<hi>gods</hi> will I ſing praiſe unto thee. This <hi>vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Appellation</hi> given to Magiſtrates, ſhould teach the <hi>Cynical Quaker,</hi> and the <hi>moroſe Anabaptiſt,</hi> with all other <hi>ejuſdem farinae,</hi> not to ſcruple at expreſſions of reverence, (ſuch as <hi>His Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſty; Dread Soveraign,</hi> and the like) toward them; and inſtruct them
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:96629:27"/>in better Manners, Breeding and Civility, than to court the <hi>Lords Vicegerents</hi> and <hi>Deputies</hi> with ſuch <hi>blunt</hi> and <hi>ruſtical</hi> Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, as if they were their Equals or Inferiours. <hi>Piety</hi> is no ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my to
<hi>Civility,</hi> not <hi>Chriſtianity</hi> to <hi>Humanity: Religion</hi> doth not forbid
<hi>good Manners.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> accounted it nothing <hi>unbeſeeming</hi> his <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolical Office,</hi> to uſe ſome Courtſhip in his <hi>Apologetical</hi> Oration before King
<hi>Agrippa.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Murder may be committed by the Tongue, as well as by the Hand. As the <hi>Seventh Commandment</hi> doth forbid not only the <hi>groſs act</hi> of Adultery, but alſo,
<list>
                  <item>1. <hi>Heart-adultery,</hi> as unclean Thoughts.</item>
                  <item>2. <hi>Eye-adultery,</hi> as wanton Glances.</item>
                  <item>3. <hi>Ear-adulterie,</hi> as hearkening to obſcene diſcourſe.</item>
                  <item>4. <hi>Hand-adultery,</hi> wanton Dalliances.</item>
                  <item>5. <hi>Lip-adultery,</hi> as unholy Kiſſes.</item>
                  <item>6. <hi>Tongue-adultery,</hi> Laſcivious ſpeech, and uttering Ribal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>So the <hi>Sixth Commandment, Thou ſhalt not kill,</hi> doth extend not only to the actual embruing the hands in the bloud of men, but alſo,
<list>
                  <item>1.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.22. 1 <hi>John.</hi> 3.15.</note> To
<hi>Heart-murder,</hi> raſh anger, envy, hatred, and all inor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinate paſſions and degrees of Murder. Wherefore, ſaith <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,</hi> curſe not the King in thy thought; for a Bird of the Air ſhall carry the voice,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Eccl.</hi> 10.20.</note> and that which hath wings, ſhall tell the Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</item>
                  <item>2.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.22.</note> To <hi>Tongue-murder.</hi> But I ſay unto you, that whoſoever ſhall ſay unto his Brother (<hi>Racha, i. e.</hi> ſhall <hi>thou</hi> him, ſaith <hi>Chryſoſtom,</hi> ſhall call him <hi>ſilly ſhallow Fellow, that wanteth Brains,</hi> ſaith <hi>Irenae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi>) ſhall be in danger of the Council; and whoſoever ſhall ſay, <hi>Thou Fool,</hi> ſhall be in danger of Hell-ſire. So that ſcornful and reproachful Speeches of, or unto a King, do amount to a kind of Murder of him.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>There are three things of King <hi>Sauls,</hi> which <hi>David</hi> ſeems to account Sacred. His <hi>Life,</hi> His <hi>Good Name,</hi> and His <hi>Robes.</hi> We read of ſome that
<hi>despiſed Saul,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Sa.</hi> 10.27.</note> and brought him <hi>no Preſents;</hi> but they are called <hi>Sons of Belial</hi> for it.</p>
            <p>How inexcuſable are thoſe, whoſe <hi>teeth</hi> are as <hi>spears</hi> and arrows, and their <hi>tongues</hi> as <hi>ſharp ſwords,</hi> to wound the Reputation of Princes.</p>
            <p>The Apoſtle <hi>Jude</hi> ranketh thoſe among the <hi>Black Hereticks</hi> of
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:96629:27"/>the laſt daies, who <hi>deſpiſe Dominion,</hi> and <hi>ſpeak evil of Dignities,</hi> or <hi>blaſpheme Glories,</hi> as the Greek words <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie; and condemneth them by the example of <hi>Michael the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>angel,</hi> who when contending with the Devil, he diſputed about the Body of <hi>Moſes,</hi> durſt not bring againſt him a <hi>railing accuſation,</hi> but ſaid, The Lord rebuke thee. If an <hi>Angel of Heaven</hi> would not <hi>rail</hi> at the <hi>Devil of Hell,</hi> then ſurely ſuch are a kind of <hi>devils incarnate,</hi> who <hi>rail</hi> at <hi>Angels:</hi> For <hi>ſo</hi> Kings are called in Scripture. As an <hi>Angel of God,</hi> ſo is my Lord the <hi>King.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Sa.</hi> 14.17.</note>
            </p>
            <p>How was our Dread Soveraign King <hi>Charles</hi> the firſt, reviled by his Adverſaries? They ſaid unto him, as <hi>Shimei</hi> to <hi>David,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Sam.</hi>
16.7.</note> Come out thou bloudy man, thou man of <hi>Belial.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As the <hi>Papiſts cloathed</hi> that Holy Martyr <hi>John Huſſe</hi> with a <hi>coat full of painted Devils,</hi> when they bro ght him to the Stake, that he might appear <hi>odious</hi> in the eye; of the <hi>Spectators,</hi> ſo was our <hi>Royal Martyr</hi> repreſented in monſtrous ſhapes, that his death might neither be <hi>prevented</hi> not <hi>lamented. O Bleſsed King!</hi> How was thy <hi>Good name</hi> wounded with the <hi>poyſoned daggers</hi> of enemie <hi>tongues, ſet on fire in Hell?</hi> even as Queen <hi>Elizabeths</hi> was by
<hi>Jeſuites,</hi> who called her an <hi>Engliſh Wolf</hi> and <hi>Lioneſs,</hi> far ſurpaſſing in cruelty, all the <hi>Athaliahs, Maachas, Jezebels</hi> and
<hi>Herodiaſſes</hi> that ever were: <hi>Os durum!</hi> And <hi>Davids</hi> by <hi>Shimei,</hi> whom <hi>Abiſhai</hi> calleth a <hi>dead Dog,</hi> for reproaching the Lords Anointed. And again, Shall not <hi>Shimei</hi> be put to death, becauſe he curſed the Lords A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointed?
<hi>David</hi> himſelf deeply reſented the grievous curſe,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Sam.</hi>
16.9. 2 <hi>Sa.</hi> 19.21.</note> wherewith this <hi>Benjamite</hi> of <hi>Bahurim</hi> curſed him. Though out of <hi>Policy David reprieved</hi> him, during his own Reign, becauſe his Kingly Authority, being like a <hi>broken Bone newly ſet,</hi> and like a man <hi>newly recovered from a deſperate fit of Sickneſs,</hi> he durſt not <hi>ſhed Blood,</hi> though in a way of Juſtice, leſt the <hi>noiſe</hi> thereof ſhould have cauſed a <hi>ſecond Revolt</hi> of the people; and ſo <hi>broke</hi> the <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ne</hi> again in the <hi>ſame</hi> place, and brought a <hi>Relapſe</hi> into the former di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtempers which would have been <hi>doubly dangerous:</hi> yet he <hi>retain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi> the
<hi>memory</hi> of this Offence unto his <hi>dying Day,</hi> and in his <hi>Laſt Will</hi> and
<hi>Teſtament,</hi> gave a ſtrict Charge unto his Son <hi>Solomon, not to hold Shimei guiltleſs,</hi> but to bring down his hoary head to the Grave with Blood.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Famous</hi> was the example of old <hi>Quintus Fabius,</hi> who,<note place="margin">1
<hi>Kings</hi> 2.</note> his <hi>Son</hi> being <hi>Conſul,</hi> laid aſide the <hi>Robes</hi> of his <hi>Paternal Dignity;</hi> and in ſtead of <hi>demanding Reverence from</hi> him as his Son, <hi>yielded reverence to him, as a Roman Conſul.</hi> Though a Son being a
<hi>Magiſtrate,</hi> is
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:96629:28"/>not thereby <hi>diveſted</hi> of his <hi>Filial Relation,</hi> nor
<hi>priviledged</hi> from Subjection to his <hi>Father, a private man,</hi> in all
<hi>domeſtical</hi> and <hi>perſonal tranſactions</hi> between them; yet in all
<hi>publick</hi> and <hi>Political Actions,</hi> the <hi>Prerogative of Honour</hi> is due from the
<hi>Father, a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate perſon,</hi> to the <hi>Son, a Magiſtrate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Solomon</hi> indeed roſe up to meet his Mother <hi>Bathſheba,</hi> bowed unto her,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Kings</hi> 2.</note> and cauſed her to ſit down on his Right hand, but
<hi>not on his Throne,</hi> that he reſerved for himſelf. <hi>Oeconomical</hi> Relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons muſt give place to <hi>Political.</hi> Honour and Reverence being due
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Kings, it ought to be manifeſted by ſutable Expreſſions and Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtures.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fear God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.17. <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.7.</note> 
               <hi>honour the King. Render</hi> unto every one their <hi>dues, Fear,</hi> to whom <hi>Fear, Honour</hi> to whom <hi>Honour</hi> belongeth. The Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>render,</hi> not <hi>give</hi> honour, to ſhew, that it is an <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſpenſible,</hi> not an <hi>arbitrary</hi> act, a matter of
<hi>neceſſity,</hi> not of <hi>gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuity;</hi> of <hi>duty,</hi> not of <hi>Curteſie.</hi> The Vulgar, <hi>Tremellius</hi> and <hi>Beza</hi> render <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>reddite, non date;</hi> which ſignifies, <hi>debitum quod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam inexcuſabile Subditis impoſitum eſſe,</hi> as <hi>Marlorat.</hi> obſerves; and <hi>praeſtationem horum officiorum ad Juſtitiam, negationem ad inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitiam pertinere,</hi> Pareus <hi>in locum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. This Title, The Lords Anointed, doth ſignifie Gods <hi>furniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> and
<hi>qualifying of Saul,</hi> with all Gifts and Endowments, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite for the diſcharge of his Office. Aſſoon as <hi>Saul</hi> was anoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, he was turned <hi>into another man,</hi> and God gave him <hi>another heart.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Sa.</hi> 10.6, 9.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The moſt <hi>fragrant</hi> and <hi>odoriferous Spices, Myrrhe, Cynamon, Calamus</hi> and
<hi>Caſſia,</hi> were the Ingredients whereof the Anointing Oyl was compounded,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ex.</hi> 30.23.</note> to ſhew the compoſition of the ſweeteſt Gifts and Graces in him, on whom it was poured. When the Lord calleth perſons unto an Office, he will furniſh them with Gifts ſutable hereunto. When <hi>Eliſha</hi> was called from the
<hi>Plow,</hi> to be a <hi>Prophet, a double portion</hi> of the <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>Elias</hi> reſted on him. When the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> were called from their <hi>Fiſhing-nets,</hi> to be
<hi>Fiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of men,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> the Holy Ghoſt deſcends upon them. When God took <hi>David</hi> from following the <hi>Ewes</hi> great with young, to feed
<hi>Jacob</hi> his people,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Sa.</hi> 16.13. <hi>Pſ.</hi> 78. ult. 2
<hi>Sa.</hi> 14.17.</note> and <hi>Iſrael</hi> his inheritance, and turned his <hi>ſhep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herds Crook</hi> into a <hi>Royal Scepter,</hi> he cauſed alſo his Spirit to deſcend upon him, and gave him <hi>skilfulneſs</hi> to wield his Scopter, and made him wiſe <hi>as an Angel of God, to deſcern between good and evil.</hi> And God gave <hi>Solomon</hi> wiſdom and underſtanding exceeding much,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Kin.</hi> 4.19.</note> and largeneſs of heart, as the ſand of the Sea ſhore.</p>
            <pb n="49" facs="tcp:96629:28" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p n="3">3. This title, the Lords Anomted, ſignifieth the <hi>divine deſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation</hi> and
<hi>conſecration of Saul</hi> unto his Office: for <hi>Unction</hi> with <hi>holy oyl</hi> was an uſual ceremony at the <hi>inſtalment</hi> of Prophets, Prieſts and Kings, as of <hi>David, Solomon, Jehu;</hi> In alluſion whereunto Jeſus Chriſt, in reſpect of Gods deſignation of him unto the Mediato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial Office, is ſaid to be anointed, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 61.1.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Office of a King is Divine, and his perſon ſacred.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Obſerv.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>By the Divine Office of Kings,</hi> I underſtand, that the <hi>Royal function</hi> hath its <hi>Original</hi> and <hi>Inſtitution from God,</hi> that it is not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<hi>lawfull,</hi> but <hi>ſacred;</hi> not only <hi>allowed,</hi> but <hi>ordained.</hi> The
<hi>Delega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> not the Election and <hi>Donation</hi> of the
<hi>people,</hi> is the foundation of Regal authority. <hi>Civil Polity</hi> is
<hi>eſtabliſhed</hi> by a <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine ſanction.</hi> Kings reign, not only by the
<hi>Permiſſion,</hi> but alſo by the <hi>Commiſſion</hi> of God.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>By the ſacred nature of the perſons of Kings.</hi> I underſtand their
<hi>ſeparation</hi> from the <hi>common</hi> condition of other men, and their deſignation unto a <hi>peculiar office;</hi> as <hi>Aaron</hi> and his ſons, and the veſſels of the Sanctuary, with all the <hi>utenſils</hi> of the Temple, were ſet apart from a common, and conſecrated unto an holy uſe. What an horrid abomination would it have been in the Jews, to have filled the
<hi>Golden veſſels</hi> of the Sanctuary with <hi>dirt?</hi> and what a vile ſin was it in
<hi>Ahaz</hi> to cut them in pieces: So what an hainous contempt of God is it, to deſtroy the ſacred lives, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach the ſacred names of Kings, ſeeing they are the Lords A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointed? This was the reaſon that cauſed <hi>David</hi> to deteſt the murder of <hi>Saul,</hi> to diſſwade <hi>Abiſhai from it,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 1.14, 15, 16. 2
<hi>Sam.</hi> 1.7, 8, 9.</note> and to execute the <hi>Amalekite for it,</hi> notwithſtanding he ſlew him at his own requeſt, after he was mortally wounded, out of compaſſion toward him to put an end to his anguiſh and miſery.</p>
            <p>As the Lord avenged the abuſe of his <hi>Anointed Mediator;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2. 1 <hi>King.</hi> 13.4. 2 <hi>King.</hi> 2.23, 24. <hi>Numb.</hi>
19. <hi>Dan.</hi> 5.3, 4, 5 <hi>Pſal.</hi> 72.7, 8. <hi>Dan.</hi> 2.21, 37.</note> Of his
<hi>Anointed Prophets;</hi> Of his <hi>Anointed Prieſts;</hi> Of the <hi>anointed Veſſels</hi> of his Sanctuary: So will he certainly avenge all injuries offered unto his
<hi>Anointed Kings</hi> on the heads of all Traytors.</p>
            <p>Now the <hi>Divine Original</hi> of the Office of Kings is written with a <hi>Sun-beam</hi> throughout the Scripture; <hi>Promotion cometh not from the Eaſt nor from the Weſt, God is Judge.</hi> But <hi>Rom</hi> 13.1, 3, 3, 4. is <hi>inſtur omnium,</hi> where the Divine inſtitution of Magiſtracy is no leſſe then ſeven times aſſerted in ſix verſes; Twice in the firſt, Let every ſoul be ſubject unto the higher powers, for there is no power but <hi>of God.</hi> The Powers that be are <hi>ordained of God.</hi> Again, <hi>v.</hi> 2. Whoſoever reſiſteth the power, reſiſteth the <hi>Ordinance of God,</hi> and
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:96629:29"/>ſhall receive to themſelves damnation. Thrice more in <hi>v.</hi> 4, 6. The Magiſtrate is called the <hi>Miniſter of God;</hi> And <hi>v.</hi> 5. we are injoyned to be ſubject, not for wrath, but for <hi>conſcience ſake.</hi> Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to the Magiſtrates authority for conſcience ſake, doth ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe it to be <hi>bottomed</hi> and founded on a divine grant, for otherwiſe it could not oblige the conſcience. The Apoſtle inculcated this doctrine on the <hi>Romans,</hi> becauſe there were ſome turbulent ſpirits among them, who inſiſted ſo much on their Chriſtian liberty, that they thought ſubjection to ſecular powers inconſiſtent therewith. But theſe Anti-magiſtratical Libertines are in this Chapter fully confuted, and the Authority of Heathen Emperours (under whom the <hi>Romans,</hi> to whom Saint <hi>Paul</hi> wrote this Epiſtle, then lived) is clearly evinced, to be an emanation from the Almighty God, who is, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>Excellently doth Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſpeak to this purpoſe;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>De Civ. Dei,</hi> li. 5. c. 21.</note> That God who gave the regiment of a Commonwealth to <hi>Caius Ceſar, a mild</hi> and <hi>gentle</hi> Prince, gave it alſo to <hi>Marius</hi> a <hi>bloody Conſul.</hi> He that gave it to <hi>Auguſtus</hi> a <hi>mirrour</hi> of <hi>humanity,</hi> gave it unto <hi>Nero</hi> a <hi>monſter</hi> of <hi>cruelty.</hi> He that gave it unto
<hi>Vespatian,</hi> gave it unto <hi>Domitiar.</hi> He that gave it unto <hi>Conſtantine</hi> a
<hi>Religious defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> of <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> gave it alſo unto <hi>Iulian</hi> an
<hi>Author</hi> of <hi>Apoſtaſie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Jeſus Chriſt the <hi>eſſential wiſdom</hi> of the Father,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro.</hi> 8.15, 16.</note> is repreſented to ſpeak under the name of Wiſdom. And what doth he ſpeak? Why this, <hi>By me Kings reign, and Princes decree juſtice. By me Princes rule, even Nobles, and all the Iudges of the earth. By me,</hi> i.e. by my
<hi>Approbation,</hi> by my <hi>Commiſsion,</hi> by my <hi>Protection,</hi> and by my
<hi>Direction</hi> and <hi>benediction</hi> Kings reign.</p>
            <p>God was diſpleaſed with <hi>Iſrael</hi> for asking a King,<note place="margin">Object.
<hi>1.</hi> Sol.</note> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 8.7.</p>
            <p>The Lords diſpleaſure againſt <hi>Iſrael</hi> for their requeſt, did not ariſe from his <hi>improbation</hi> of <hi>Monarchical</hi> Government, but from <hi>Iſraels contempt</hi> of <hi>Theocratical</hi> Government; for from the time of <hi>Moſes,</hi> untill the daies of
<hi>Samuel,</hi> they lived under a <hi>Theocraſie.</hi> God did exert his power in an extraordinary and miraculous man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, in raiſing up Judges to deliver them out of the hands of their enemies; but they being grown <hi>weak</hi> in <hi>faith,</hi> and <hi>weary</hi> of this
<hi>immediate dependance</hi> on God, and truſting too much on an arm of fleſh, cry out for a King: wherewith God is indeed diſpleaſed, becauſe of their <hi>audacious preſumption</hi> in <hi>limiting</hi> and preſcribing unto him, becauſe of the <hi>itch</hi> and <hi>pride</hi> of their hearts in deſiring to be <hi>conformed</hi> unto other Nations; and becauſe of their deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of God himſelf,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Sam.</hi> 8.7.</note> that he ſhould not reign over them: but not
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:96629:29"/>by reaſon of any diſtaſte againſt the Office of a King, which he after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward bleſſed for the protection of his people <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Though the Office of <hi>Saul,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Object. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> it being immediatly by God himſelf conferred on him, was Divine, and his perſon therefore ſacred: yet Kings now, wanting this immediate election, cannot claim the like Prerogatives.</p>
            <p>The Texts before quoted do ſufficiently confute this Objection,<note place="margin">Sol.</note> to wit <hi>Matth.</hi> 22.21. <hi>Dan.</hi> 2.37. <hi>Prov.</hi> 8.15, 16. <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.1, 2. However I ſhall add theſe three things.
<list>
                  <item>1. That many Kings of <hi>Iſrael</hi> (whoſe perſons were no leſſe ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred then the others) were neither extraordinarily elected nor conſecrated, but took poſſeſſion of the Kingdom, by <hi>hereditary ſucceſsion.</hi> For all Kings were not anointed, but only thoſe in whom the <hi>Royal line began,</hi> or was <hi>broken:</hi> Only the firſt of a Family was anointed, except in the caſe of diſſention, where was required a renewed unction.</item>
                  <item>2. <hi>Cyrus</hi> an <hi>Heathen King</hi> is called <hi>the Lords anointed,</hi> Iſa.
45.1. Thus ſaith the Lord to his Anointed, to <hi>Cyrus.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. As the Office of Miniſters is ſacred, notwithſtanding they want that immediate Call, which the Prophets and Apoſtles had, ſo likewiſe is the Office of Kings, notwithſtanding they want ſuch an immediatly divine inauguration, as <hi>Saul</hi> and <hi>David</hi> had.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Donatiſts, Libertines,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Object. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>Anabaptists</hi> and <hi>Millenaries</hi> have laid the <hi>Ax</hi> to the very <hi>root</hi> of civil <hi>Magiſtracy;</hi> holding, that though God allotted Kings and Rulers unto the Jews, while the Church was in its <hi>infancy, minority</hi> and <hi>nonage,</hi> yet now ſuch ſervile ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection doth not beſeem that perfection and liberty, which the Goſpel hath introduced.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>John</hi> 8.32. <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.1.</note> 
               <hi>You ſhall know the truth, and the truth ſhall make you free. Stand fast in the liberty wherewith Chriſt hath made you free.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whereunto ſhall I liken this generation?<note place="margin">Sol.</note> They are like unto water in a Pot, which boyleth over much, runneth into the fire, which being quenched therewith, the remainder of the water boyleth not at all: So theſe affecting greater wiſdom, perfection, and liberty then is meet, became very fools, and bondſlaves to their luſts. Thoſe texts,
<hi>Joh.</hi> 8.32. <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.1. ſpeak of the freedom of Chriſtians from the reign of ſin, power of the Law, and domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the devil, and the yoke of Jewiſh ceremonies; not of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emption from obedience to the civil Magiſtrate. <hi>Chriſtian liberty</hi> and <hi>civil ſubjection</hi> are not <hi>inconſiſtent,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> but <hi>ſweetly meet</hi> and <hi>kiſſe</hi> each other. The Pſalmiſt ſpeaking of the times of the Goſpel, doth
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:96629:30"/>not exhort Kings to <hi>pull off</hi> their <hi>Crowns,</hi> and to <hi>lay down</hi> their <hi>Scepters,</hi> but only to manage their Government in the <hi>fear of God,</hi> and to do <hi>homage</hi> unto Chriſt, <hi>v.</hi> 11, 12.</p>
            <p>Magiſtracy is as neceſſary for the preſervation of humane ſocie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, as Air,
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ater, or any of the four elements for the ſuſtentation of our natural lives.</p>
            <p>And as the Goſpel doth not <hi>aboliſh</hi> civil Government, ſo neither doth it
<hi>tranſlate</hi> it from men, and <hi>devolve</hi> it on Jeſus Chriſt. It was the
<hi>ſtumbling block</hi> of the <hi>Jews,</hi> that they expected a <hi>temporal Kingdom,</hi> by the coming of the Meſſiah, a <hi>manumiſsion</hi> out of their <hi>bondage</hi> to the
<hi>Romans,</hi> and a <hi>reſtauration</hi> of the <hi>Kingdom of Iſrael</hi> unto that
<hi>primitive glory</hi> and <hi>ſplendour</hi> wherein it <hi>flouriſhed</hi> under
<hi>David</hi> and <hi>Solomon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let not <hi>that</hi> Government be <hi>affixed</hi> to Chriſt, which he himſelf
<hi>diſclaims:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>John</hi> 18.36.</note> 
               <hi>My Kingdom is not of this world,</hi> that is, not an earthly Kingdom, nor the <hi>Adminiſtrations</hi> thereof converſant about ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal affairs, neither civil nor criminal. Not <hi>Civil,</hi> for when a man deſired him to divide an inheritance between him and his brother, he ſharply rebukes him, ſaying, <hi>Man, who made me a Judge or divider between you?</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi>
12.14.</note> Neither would he <hi>intermeddle</hi> in <hi>criminal</hi> matters, but refuſed to pronounce ſentence on the woman taken in <hi>Adultery,</hi> John 8.11.</p>
            <p>The Apoſtle reprehendeth the Diviſions of the Church of <hi>Corinth; Every one of you ſaith, I am for Paul,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.12.</note> 
               <hi>I am for Apollo, I am for C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>phas, and I am of Chriſt:</hi> Theſe laſt ſort are blamed, becauſe out of an irregular zeal to advance the honour of Chriſt, they decried his Miniſters. In like manner may the <hi>State-diviſions</hi> of <hi>England</hi> be reprehended; <hi>One</hi> ſaith, <hi>I am for a Commonwealth,</hi> another, <hi>I am for a Committee of Safety,</hi> another, <hi>I am for a Protector,</hi> and a fourth ſort, <hi>I am for Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All theſe deſerve ſharp reproof, even the Fifth Monarchy aſſertors alſo, notwithſtanding they cry out for Chriſt; becauſe by reaſon of their raſh zeal, or rather
<hi>wild ſire,</hi> they take an <hi>inordinate</hi> courſe to advance Chriſt, namely, by footing out the civil Magiſtrate, who is <hi>a Minister of God for our good.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.4.</note> How was this <hi>desperatly, bloodily,</hi> yea
<hi>blaſphemouſly,</hi> but, bleſſed be God, <hi>ſucceſſeleſly</hi> attempted in
<hi>England,</hi> by perſons that would have <hi>entitled Jeſus Christ</hi> to their
<hi>murders;</hi> as if he that did <hi>ſhed his own blood for our ſakes,</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighted in ſhedding our blood. Theſe, under a pretence of fighting for <hi>King Jeſus</hi> did indeed fight for <hi>King Beelzebub.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>light of Nature</hi> confuteth this <hi>Antimagiſtratical</hi> opinion. As there is no Nation <hi>ſo barbarous,</hi> as to acknowledge <hi>no God,</hi> ſo neither as to acknowledge
<hi>no Magiſtrate.</hi> Many <hi>irrational</hi> creatures ſeem by a <hi>natural inſtinct</hi> to have the <hi>ſhadow</hi> of <hi>Government</hi> amongſt them: There is a
<hi>Maſter Bee</hi> Had <hi>Adam</hi> continued in innocency, <hi>ſuperiority</hi> and
<hi>inferiority</hi> among mankind would have continued with him. Yea there ſeems to be an
<hi>order</hi> among the very <hi>Angels</hi> themſelves; for we read of an <hi>Archangel,</hi> Jude v. 9.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
